<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Fatall prudence, or, Democrates, the unfortunate heroe a novell / translated out of French.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 175 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 124 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A40978</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F544</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13153082</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13153082</idno>
            <idno type="VID">98116</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A40978)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98116)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 416:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Fatall prudence, or, Democrates, the unfortunate heroe a novell / translated out of French.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 199, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J. Bennet for R. Bentley and M. Magnes ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1679.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translation of an unidentified work in French.</note>
                  <note>First English ed. Cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
                  <note>Pages 8-9, 75-76 and 169 are stained; pages 166-193 are faded and have print show-through in filmed copy. Pages 160-end photographed from British Library copy and inserted at the end.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement on p. [1] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:98116:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Licenſed,</hi> May <hi>9. 1678.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Ro. L'Eſtrange.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:98116:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Fatall Prudence, OR,</hi> DEMOCRATES, <hi>THE Unfortunate Heroe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Novell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tranſlated out of French.</p>
            <p>LONDON, <hi>Printed by</hi> J. Bennet <hi>for</hi> R. Bentley <hi>and</hi> M. Magnes <hi>in</hi> Ruſſell-ſtreet <hi>near</hi> Covent-Garden, <hi>1679.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:98116:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:98116:2"/>
            <head>Fatall Prudence, OR, <hi>DEMOCRATES,</hi> THE Unfortunate Heroe.</head>
            <head type="sub">A Novell.</head>
            <p>THe Unfortunate Heroe of this Hiſtory, having through many conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſervices merited the good Graces of his <hi>King,</hi> and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf honour'd with his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, and being poſſeſt of a very large eſtate by his liberalities, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended a while to make ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection within himſelf of that glorious Rank and Eminence he was in at Court by his Prince, and to examine to what thoſe of his quality were expoſed. He
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:98116:3"/>look'd on the favour he had, not as thoſe uſe to do who are yet in proſperity, he had better eyes then your generality of favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites, who know not that it is deceitful, but when they can no longer keep it from deſtroying them. He ſaw very well that it was inconſtant, and that he ought to miſtruſt it, that it ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd to all the dangers immagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable thoſe whom it raiſes to the higheſt dignity and honours, and that in giving them riches and credit, it makes their beſt friends become their Emulators, and renders all thoſe inferiour to them enviouſly jealous of their glory and happineſs. The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of all theſe things made <hi>Democrates</hi> (for ſo was this unfortunate Heroe call'd) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd to take a very ſtrict care of his leaſt accounts, and of all his words: that ſo he might not raiſe
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:98116:3"/>to himſelf any enemies, nor give thoſe, whom the noiſe of his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune might make malicious, any occaſion of becoming prejudiciall to him, though they ſhould dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly watch for an Opportunity to be ſo; nor to undertake any thing which he had not very well exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined, and to follow the Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of prudence, when thoſe that were equal to him never did conſult it.</p>
            <p>He had ſcarce made this reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, but the Duke <hi>Nicanor,</hi> brother to the King his Maſter, deſir'd him to aſſiſt him in his Love, and acquainted him with the deſign he had to marry <hi>Fulci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ana,</hi> a Lady that was one of the greateſt beauties that ſhone in the Kingdome, and daughter to one of the firſt Officers of the Crown, but whom he could not marry without blemiſhing his quality, becauſe ſhe had not received ſo
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:98116:4"/>many advantages from fortune as to place her in the number of Princeſſes, as ſhe had from Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which had made her one of the Charming beauties in the world. This confidence gave <hi>Democrates</hi> a very great trouble, for he well knew prudence ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times was altogether unprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, in that it could not give hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Councells. But yet, after he had ſufficiently conſulted what he ought to do, he thought that to oblige at once both the King his Maſter, and the Duke <hi>Nicanor,</hi> it was his duty to diſſwade the Prince from a deſign that would be a diſreputation to his glory, &amp; contrary to the eſteems that all perſons, even the higheſt digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied of the Kingdome, had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd of him. He told him therefore, he thought he ſhould not deſerve the honour he did him, if he ſhould diſguiſe his
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:98116:4"/>ſentiments to him, whereupon he repreſented to him in terms that were as preſſing as reſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, all that might oblige him to leave off ſuch a deſign, and that he could not marry <hi>Fulciana</hi> without leſſening himſelf ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly, and without betraying his quality, and lowering that great reputation he had acquir'd. The Prince, after he had heard all his reaſons, did as moſt Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers uſe to do when they are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded of the truth of what is told them, that is to ſay, approve them ſighing, and told <hi>Democra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes</hi> he was not then in a condition to hearken to his councells, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it was not in his power to follow them.</p>
            <p>A little after the King hearing of the Amours of his Brother, and fearing he would make an alli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance ſo prejudiciall to his quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, told <hi>Democrates,</hi> that as he
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:98116:5"/>had always aſſum'd the care of his fortune, ſo he would alſo take upon him that of his marriage, and give him ſtill new acceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons with the beautifull <hi>Fulciana,</hi> though <hi>Democrates</hi> had not as yet ingag'd his heart to any, and had beheld in that perſon all he was able to deſire, yet the reſolution of the King to marry him gave him a very ſenſible affliction; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Duke <hi>Nicanor,</hi> who was paſſionately fir'd with the ſame charms, had made a Diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of his Love to him, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo deſir'd him to ſerve him in it. He endeavour'd nevertheleſſe to conceal from the King's eyes the ſurpriſe that that diſcourſe was the occaſion of to him, and after he had return'd him his acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgments for all the favours and kindneſs he for him, and teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied to him that he was ready to do all he ſhould command him,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:98116:5"/>he made him to foreſee that he had no mind to marry <hi>Fulciana,</hi> but through obedience; and that he had not yet any deſign to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſe of himſelf, nor any inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for that fair one; the King, who was firmly reſolv'd upon that marriage, did not ſeem to apprehend any thing of what <hi>Democrates</hi> would fain have had him underſtood, and told him he was glad to ſee him in the reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of obliging him. <hi>Democrates</hi> went away from him very much troubled, and was muſing all the reſt of the day, and all the night, about the means to keep himſelf in the good graces of the King, and in thoſe of the Duke <hi>Nicanor;</hi> but Prudence not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving furniſh'd him with any, or at leaſt having given him but ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry weak ones, he went the next day betimes to wait upon the Duke, who no ſooner preceiv'd
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:98116:6"/>him coming into his chamber, but he lookt upon him with eyes full of threatning, and told him in a very diſdainful manner, and which ſhow'd a great deal of ſcorn, <q>I do not any longer won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, why you were able to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade me not to marry <hi>Fulciana,</hi> a Rivall ought not to give any other Councels to his Rival; but you ought to regard your difference that is betwixt us, not to abuſe my confidence, to ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice all your flame to me, and not to demand of the King the object of my vows, and that of my earneſt deſires. You may, added he with a look capable to make a heart of the greateſt aſſurance and reſolution trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, preſs on this marriage if you are weary of living; but let heaven be my witneſs, you ſhall ſooner be in the arms of death, then in thoſe of <hi>Fulciana.</hi>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:98116:6"/>Death, replied <hi>Democrates</hi> to him, ſhall not beget any fear in me in the eſtate to which I am reduced, and I do ſo much the more earneſtly deſire it, as I ſee it is only that which can deliver me from the confuſion into which I am caſt, by the confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence you have made me of your Love, and that extream kindneſs the King has for me; ſince that that confidence makes me to paſs for a traitor, and for one ungrateful, without having merited that name; and that the Bounties of the King, in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowing upon me more then I deſire, makes me to paſs for their Rival, without ever loving the object of their flame; but to ſhow you, continued he, that all I ſay is true, if you can finde out any means to prevent my marrying of <hi>Fulciana,</hi> and keep the King from being diſpleas'd
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:98116:7"/>with me for it, I proteſt to you I'll ſubſcribe to whatever you are pleas'd to have me, and I will likewiſe, to aſſiſt you, do all that ever I am able, without appearing ungrateful to the Kings bounties, and rebellious to his commands.</q> This diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, far from giving the Duke <hi>Nicanor</hi> any Joy, only ſerv'd to increaſe the trouble he had in his breaſt; he knew very well that a Rival was not all he had to fear, and that the King having heard of his paſſion, did not preſs <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mocrates</hi> to marry <hi>Fulciana,</hi> but only to prevent his marrying of her; this conſideration made him almoſt immoveable; fear and grief took poſſeſſion of his ſoul, and for ſome time kept him from ſpeaking; but after his grief had loſt a little of its violence, and he was ſomewhat come to himſelf, he told <hi>Democrates,</hi> he would
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:98116:7"/>think upon what he had ſaid, and that on his ſide nothing ſhould be ſpared to make things ſucceed according to his deſires. <hi>Demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates</hi> being retired, the Duke opened his breaſt again to grief, and was buried in a profound ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, which he got not out of till he had light upon a way to divert the blow which threatned him. He reſolv'd with himſelf, the more eaſily to attain the end of his deſign, to remove <hi>Democrates</hi> from the high place he held in the King's affection, and therein to follow the examples of all great men, who ſacrifice to their intereſts all thoſe who ſerve them, and who little are troubled for the misfortunes that befall them, ſo they can but have what they deſire: this made our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpairing Lover go and tell the King that <hi>Democrates</hi> proclaim'd openly that he had more hatred
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:98116:8"/>then Love for <hi>Fulciana,</hi> that he had rather loſe his favour, then marry her, that he knew how to turn aſide the ſtroke, and that it was more then he could do, to make him buy, at the expence of his heart, the bounties he had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived from him; and that his ſervices having merited thoſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, it was not juſt that he ſhould buy them over again, or rather ſacrifice himſelf to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve 'em; the King did ſo much the more readily believe this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, as he began to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that <hi>Democrates</hi> had made him foreſee he would not marry <hi>Fulciana,</hi> but only in obedience to him, which ſo incens'd him, that a little more would have made him been immediately ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſted. After the Duke <hi>Nicanor</hi> had perſwaded the King his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther what he had a minde to make him believe, <hi>Fulciana,</hi> the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:98116:8"/>Father of his Miſtreſs, who joyn'd with him in the intrigue, came by his order to ſpeak to the King and to conjure him not to give his daughter to a man, who only had a ſcorn &amp; an averſion for her; he would with all his heart moſt readily have conſented to this match, if the heart of <hi>Democrates</hi> had been diſpos'd to it, but that ſince he diſcovered by thoſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes that he would never have any Love for her, and that he would not marry her but by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint, he intreated him that he might have the ſentiments of a father, and that he might not conſent to the unhappineſs of a daughter, whom he moſt tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly loved. As the King was going to reply to him, <hi>Fulciana</hi> entered to act the perſonage of the Duke <hi>Nicanor,</hi> her Father and ſhe had reſolv'd on beforehand to have her repreſent. <hi>Fulcian</hi> had no
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:98116:9"/>ſooner perceiv'd her, but he feign'd to be much ſurpriz'd, and ask'd her if ſhe came to ſtir up the Kings pity, and to divert the miſery ſhe was threatn'd with. <q>I come, replied ſhe to him, mau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger all the averſion I have for <hi>Democrates,</hi> and all the hatred he declares he has for me, to ſhow I can obey the commands of my Prince, and to tell him I am ready to follow his Laws. Ah! childe, did <hi>Fulcian</hi> anſwer her, think upon what you are doing, and do not promiſe that which you may have cauſe to repent of, and do not ſo raſhly run to meet your miſery. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I very well know, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd ſhe, that I am likely to be the moſt wretched perſon in the world, in marrying him whom my Prince would give me, yet I will never relent, that I have obeyed my King: it is a crime to
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:98116:9"/>refuſe him any thing; he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of me my heart, and it is to him that I give it, and not to <hi>Democrates,</hi> though I am rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to marry him. Ah, Sir! cry'd out <hi>Fulcian,</hi> throwing himſelf at the Kings feet, have pity of a childe, who to obey you, has none for her ſelf; and if my prayers and tears cannot ſoften you, ſuffer your ſelf to be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come by her generoſity, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent your ſelf with her obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe Diſcourſes ſo ſurpriz'd the King, that after he had ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mir'd the power that <hi>Fulciana</hi> had over her ſelf, he ſent them both away without reſolving on any thing, and told them he would adviſe what to do.</p>
            <p>Whilſt all theſe things were hapning, the Duke <hi>Nicanor,</hi> whom Love had inſpir'd with all theſe ſtratagems and deviſes, waited
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:98116:10"/>the iſſue of them with impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; for he had not made <hi>Fulci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ana</hi> ſay, that ſhe was ready to marry <hi>Democrates,</hi> but that ſo their actions might be the leſs obſerv'd, and that there might be no ſuſpicion either of the Love that that fair one had for him, or of the hopes he gave her of mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying her: but at the ſame time, after ſuch an acknowledgment to prevent the Kings preſſing on the marriage which he fear'd, and alſo that it ſhould not be accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh'd, he cauſed the Father of <hi>Fulciana</hi> to oppoſe it, and to drive things off ſo long till he had abſolutely remov'd <hi>Democrates</hi> from the place he held in the Kings affection, and had made all the world believe that he had a moſt invincible hatred for <hi>Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciana,</hi> he hop'd if all theſe things did not cauſe the breaking off the match which he fear'd, they
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:98116:10"/>would at leaſt ſerve to gain him time; and indeed he did obtain a great deal; for the King teſtify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſo much anger againſt <hi>Demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erates,</hi> that it was a long while be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he was willing to permit him to come into his preſence. On the other ſide, ſeeing himſelf yet but ill confirm'd in his Eſtates, and <hi>Fulcian</hi> having very great credit, and ſeveral conſiderable friends, he was afraid to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke him; ſo that all theſe things, joyned to the thoughts he had, that ſince <hi>Fulciana</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to marry <hi>Democrates,</hi> ſhe was not ſo much beloved by the Duke his brother as they had been perſwading him, troubled him exceedingly, and made it a long time before he could de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine any thing. He found he was not likely to get out of the incertainty and confuſion which he perceiv'd himſelf involv'd in,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:98116:11"/>if he had not reſolved to ſend for <hi>Democrates,</hi> and to diſcourſe with him in private, to ſee if he could not perſwade him to ſtifle, or at leaſt to conceal the hatred he thought he had for <hi>Fulciana;</hi> but he was extraordinarily ſurprized to learn from his mouth, that he found himſelf more diſpoſed to Love then hatred, and that he begged of him not to demand the cauſe of that coldneſs and indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence he had ſhown the firſt time he had ſpoken to him of that mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage. That Diſcourſe made the King ſuſpect ſome part of the truth, and he obliged <hi>Democrates</hi> to tell him the reſt, which he thought he might do, without any imprudence, and without looſing the reſpect he owed to the Duke <hi>Nicanor,</hi> after what he had done for him, the King having learnt all, confeſſed he had acted prudently, and not being any
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:98116:11"/>longer able to doubt of the Love which his Brother had for <hi>Fulcia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> and fearing that that fair one would ſuffer her ſelf to be van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhed by the charms of ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, again told <hi>Democrates</hi> that he would have him marry her, and that he would protect him from the fury of his Brother: which he promiſed, not knowing any means how to turn it off.</p>
            <p>The Duke <hi>Nicanor</hi> having learnt this news, ſought every where for <hi>Democrates,</hi> to immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late him to his Love, and to his choler; but not having found him, he reſolved to marry <hi>Fulcia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi> privately, and afterwards to declare his marriage to the King. He communicated that deſign to <hi>Fulcian,</hi> who ſeeing by that his Ambition ſatisfyed, told him he might be married without fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any thing, and if the King reſolv'd to make his marriage
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:98116:12"/>void, he would then diſcover to him that he could not bring any into his family who might pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure him more conſiderable ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages then his daughter, and that he had ſtill need of <hi>Fulcian</hi> and his friends.</p>
            <p>There wanted no more to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blige the the Duke of <hi>Nicanor</hi> to marry the adorable <hi>Fulciana,</hi> which he did in the preſence of ſeveral conſiderable witneſſes. In the mean time news was brought to the King of it, who notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding cauſed her to be ſought for, to make her marry <hi>Democra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes</hi> in his preſence whom ſhe was already married to. For indeed he could not give any belief to the certainty of it, untill it was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed to him by the Duke his Brother, who preſently came to throw himſelf at his knees, and to intreat him to conſent to his marriage. <q>He told him he knew
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:98116:12"/>very well he was much to blame in that he had done it without his knowledge; but he had not the power to be Maſter of his paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, which he had a long time contended with, and that it was impoſſible for him to reſiſt the violence of his Love, and to deny his hand (where he had ſacrific'd his heart) to the moſt beautiful perſon in the world: the King repli'd to him, that for a Miſtreſs he could not make choice of one who might be more advantagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to him, and he doubted not but <hi>Fulciana</hi> had that honour; but that he did not believe ſhe was his wife, and he knew very well that he was, too prudent, and had too much Spirit to do ſo great an injury to his Quality and Eminence. He replied to him, that what he told him was true, and named him all thoſe perſons who had ſeen him mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried.</q>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:98116:13"/>The King ſtood immova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble at this diſcourſe, with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpite and choler in his eyes, and eſpecially in his Countenance; but yet he durſt not let them break out but lightly, nor go to break off ſo unequal a marriage; becauſe he ſaw very well that <hi>Fulcian</hi> having had that temerity to permit it, he had likewiſe more friends and greater power then he imagined, and that he could not oppoſe him without raiſing up againſt him a party of the moſt conſiderable Grandees in the Realm, which was the cauſe that he pardoned his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and that he agreed to his marriage rather through policy, then out of any ſatisfaction he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by it.</p>
            <p>The choler and deſpite of the King, (being thus forcibly ſtifled in him, as that he durſt not let it break forth either againſt the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:98116:13"/>Duke his Brother, or againſt <hi>Fulcina,</hi>) fell upon <hi>Democrates;</hi> he was greatly inraged againſt him, and blamed his prudence, which he but a little before did ſo highly value. He told him that he was the cauſe of the injury his Brother had done to his blood, and ſo deprived him of his favour, but yet without baniſhing him the Court, where he afterwards lookt upon him for ſometime, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> with a great deal of indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Democrates,</hi> perceiving that he was deprived of the good graces of his Prince, and that he had no favourable place in the minde of the Duke <hi>Nicanor,</hi> becauſe when he had juſtifyed himſelf of what that Duke had ſaid to the King, he had conſented to the marriage of <hi>Fulciana,</hi> knew at his own ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence, that when misfortune is obſtinately reſolved to purſue a
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:98116:14"/>perſon, prudence ſignifies very little, and how profitable ſoever it is at other times, one conſults it then but in vain. <q>Is there any one, ſays he, (in bewailing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with his friends at the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace that had hapned to him,) to whom prudence can be favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable; when he is forced to do evil, whatever it is poſſible for him to do? and when he runs the ſame danger in not purſuing its direction? Thoſe whoſe lives, fate has determined ſhall be mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable, and yet who have the Election given them of two or three puniſhments, have enough to conſult of prudence to know what they ſhall do, and not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding at laſt they are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitated to chooſe one puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Fortune has now almoſt put me into this condition, I could not conſent to what the King-commanded me, without
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:98116:14"/>provoking the Duke <hi>Nicanor,</hi> nor conſent to what Duke <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canor</hi> would have me, without incenſing the King; and my un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happineſſe was ſuch, that I did draw upon my ſelf his anger in doing nothing.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Five or ſix moneths were ſpent before <hi>Democrates</hi> was reſtored to the good graces of his Prince, but at laſt the King, conſidering that the Marriage of his brother had been more profitable to him then he had imagined, and that <hi>Fulcian</hi> had hindred a great many diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented perſons from breaking out into any violences, &amp; had brought them to their duty and ſubmiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, looked upon this prudent un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate man with as good an eye as ever he had done before his diſgrace; but he did not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore him to his confidence; he loved him without making him his favourite, that place cannot be
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:98116:15"/>eaſily rendred to thoſe who have once loſt it, through the good or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that thoſe obſerve, who by their wit and happy addreſſe have known how to make themſelves Maſters of it.</p>
            <p>Our Heroe who was not whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſatisfied with the reparation that Fortune then did make him, perceiving himſelf much leſs em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed then when he had been his Princes favourite, and was intruſted with all his ſecrets, was reſolved to try whether the perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions of Love were any thing pleaſanter then thoſe his evil for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune cauſed him, and gave up himſelf to be charm'd with the beauties of <hi>Seſtiana,</hi> the Daughter of Count <hi>Seſtianes,</hi> who was not altogether ſo happy in point of Eſtate as he, but who was of as illuſtrious a Family: Although his paſſion was very violent, yet as he did nothing but with a great
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:98116:15"/>deal of prudence, he was reſolved to know before he would declare it, if it were likely to be appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of, and would not make a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of his flame, before that his actions, his ſervices, and his regards had made the judication. <hi>Seſtianes</hi> began to perceive his love, and wiſhed with all his heart that his tongue would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm what his eyes did ſeem to tell him, when her father was ſollicited for her by a conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble perſon: <hi>Seſtianes</hi> fearing leſt he might fall off, gave him his word before he had ever acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted his daughter with it, and came not to tell her the news till after the marriage was concluded on. This fair one, who began to have ſome inclinations for <hi>Demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates,</hi> received it with a very cold indifference; but ſhe always told her father that ſhe was ready to be led by his commands, which
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:98116:16"/>ſhe looked upon as her duty to do, as much becauſe of the obedience ſhe owed him, as becauſe that <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mocrates</hi> had not as yet declared the paſſion he had for her.</p>
            <p>This unhappy Lover whom Prudence had always betrayed, had ſcarcely learnt this ſad and afflictive news, but he came to wait upon <hi>Seſtiana</hi> to make a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of his love to her; She had no ſooner perceived it but ſhe was inſtantly ſenſible of ſo great an emotion, and ſo violent a grief in her breaſt, that it was plainly remarkable in her face. <hi>Democrates</hi> on his part appeared ſo planet-ſtruck, that he could not ſo much as get one word, which occaſioned them a great while to do nothing but keep their eyes fixed upon one another, without having the power to ſpeak a ſyllable; but at laſt <hi>Demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates</hi> broke the ſilence, and after
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:98116:16"/>he had eaſed himſelf of two or three ſighs which lay very heavy upon his ſoul, and which made the afflicted fair one ſufficiently to know the trouble he had in it, he ſaid to her; <q>Is it poſſible, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, that what I have now late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly heard is true, and that you are within theſe few days to be led to the Altar by— Yes, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported ſhe to him in a little kinde of rage, I am, ſince you have been willing to permit it: Pardon me, my Lord, replied ſhe immediatly, repenting that ſhe ſpoke to him in that man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and do not attribute it to any thing but the terrible tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports of grief I have upon my ſpirit, and which do confound me, that they keep me from thinking either of what I do or ſay. Ah! Madam, did <hi>Demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates</hi> anſwer her, flinging him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf at her knees, You need not
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:98116:17"/>longer conceal from me, that I ſhould have been the happieſt man in the world, if fate which continually is perſecuting me, had not fully oppoſed it; Your eyes and mouth do tell it me; they are witneſſes you cannot diſavow; do not make them falſe, for heavens ſake, but ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer me to feel in all their extent the fatal and yet charming diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſures of learning my happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, when it is impoſſible for me to enjoy it: They will give me joy and ſadneſſe both toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the former in hearing that I have the glory to be belov'd by ſo fair and generous a perſon, and the latter in having known it too late, and in not having ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner declar'd my paſſion to you. Ah, cruel man! replied <hi>Seſtiana</hi> to him ſighing, why did you no ſooner ſpeak of it? or why do you ſpeak of it ſo late? If you
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:98116:17"/>loved me, as you ſay you did, you ought to have loved my repoſe, and not to deprive me of it, to let me believe that you have ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver had any kindeneſſe for me: The little worth there is in me, replied <hi>Democrates</hi> to her, not rendring my loſſe conſiderable, ought not to cauſe that of your repoſe; but as my loſſe is vaſtly great in loſing you, it is only I my ſelf ought to complain, and to repent that I have no ſooner diſcovered my flame to you: From whence did it then pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed, ſaid <hi>Seſtiana</hi> to him, that you were ſo long without ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of it? thoſe who demand a heart, anſwered he her, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out having merited it by their ſervices, by their love and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions, have been often ill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived; I looked on yours as too conſiderable to be hazarded; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides I was not ignorant that a
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:98116:18"/>heart does not ſacrifice its ſelf but to the knowledge it hath of the Love of its votary, and not to the demand he ſhall make of it, and that there is no beauty but refuſes it to thoſe who have not merited it by their Love and Services, unleſs ambition con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrains them to it, or that the grandeur and the illuſtrious me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of thoſe who demand it do oblige them: as likewiſe we ought not to be eſteemed Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, as ſoon as we begin our paſſion; it is time which muſt acquire that quality, and thoſe who have not diſcovered that they do with juſtice poſſeſſe it, are much to blame to pretend that they are beloved, becauſe they begin to love. The Love of a beautiful and charming per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ought not to be the conqueſt of a Gallants firſt ſigh; and thoſe who are ſo vain to believe they
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:98116:18"/>could obtain it before they have learnt to love, deſerve to meet with the higheſt ſeverity and Indignation of the fair One, whoſe heart they are ſo bold to demand. This has been it, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued <hi>Democrates,</hi> which made me forbear ſo long to diſcover the ardour with which I burn, and as I fear'd provoking you by the confeſſion of my Love, I was willing to diſpoſe your breaſt to it by dutifull ſubmiſſions, by my aſſiduities, and by a thouſand other marks of the moſt violent paſſion that ever was.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seſtiana</hi> could not hear this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe without diſmiſſing ſome ſighs, and when <hi>Democrates,</hi> had left of ſpeaking, ſhe told him, <q>that ſince ſhe had miſtruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his merit, and he had thought he could never obtain her heart before he had made himſelf wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of it by his ſervices and by
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:98116:19"/>his Love, he ought to have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented the unhappineſs that had befell him, to have demanded her of her father as ſoon as he had taken up the deſign of love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her, and afterwards to have indeavoured by his cares and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiduities to obtain her of her ſelf. Ah! Madam, replied he to her, I was not willing to ſerve my ſelf that way, but would have obtained your heart of your ſelf alone, and have had you to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it to the proofs of my Love, and not to your duty; without that, I ſhould never have thought to have the glorious ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of being beloved by ſo fair and beautiful a perſon, though poſſibly you would have conſented without any trouble to marry me; I ſhould not have known how to diſtinguiſh your Love from your Obedience, but ſhould have always thought you
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:98116:19"/>ought to hate me, not doubting but I ſhould have merited your hatred, for having demanded you of any other beſides your ſelf.</q> They continued ſtill ſome time together in disburthening themſelves of their ſighs, and in bewailing their unhappineſs, and when they were taking their leaves of one another, <hi>Seſtiana</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſes <hi>Democrates</hi> to go and declare to her Father the Love he had for her, and ſhe deſired him at the ſame time not to ſee her any more, if he could obtain no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing from him: this unfortunate Lover had no ſooner left her, but he went to diſcover his paſſion to <hi>Seſtianes,</hi> who told him, that he did as much reſent the diſpleaſure as himſelf, in that he had not ſooner declared his paſſion, but now his Daughters marriage was too far gone to break it off. <hi>Demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates,</hi> after this anſwer that he
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:98116:20"/>had foreſeen, return'd as affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, as you may imagine, you your ſelves ſhould be in the like circumſtances, and a few days af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he had the cruel diſſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to ſee a perſon married whom he loved even to adoration, and by whom he was likewiſe greatly beloved. Then did he repent the time he had loſt before he had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared his Love, and then did he a thouſand times deteſt the pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence that had councell'd him to act in that manner.</p>
            <p>Fortune, which till then had ſtill ſeem'd to repent for all the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultations ſhe had made over our Heroe, and for all the miſerys ſhe had procured him, ſeem'd in this to repent more then ever; ſince that <hi>Seſtiana</hi> became a wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow within three months after ſhe was married. The death of her Husband gave <hi>Democrates</hi> a freſh opportunity to make his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:98116:20"/>to her. <hi>Seſtianes</hi> appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved both of his viſits, and of the addreſs he made to his Daughter, and there was only a waiting for the expiration of the year of her mourning to celebrate the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage; when, on a ſudden, For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, which was reſolved to be no longer favourable to this Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, or rather which had not ſeem'd to be favourable to him, but to make him the more deeply ſenſible of the afflictions ſhe was preparing for him, declar'd her ſelf abſolutely his enemy.</p>
            <p>Affairs were then in this po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, when <hi>Theomedes,</hi> a Prince of the blood, and a near relation of the Kings, received this Letter from one of the Officers of the Army.</p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:98116:21"/>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>To Prince <hi>THEOMEDES.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>BEing now juſt upon the point of go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to be accountable to the Gods for my actions, and ſeeing my ſelf very near my laſt moment of life, I thought it was my duty to reveal to you a buſineſs that concerns you very much. A few days ſince one of my ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance came to demand of me whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I would joyn in a conſpiracy that was contrived againſt your Life: he would not acquaint me with the names of the confederates, but all that I could draw from him was, that he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved that <hi>Democrates</hi> was one of the Number, becauſe he was too great a friend to thoſe who had ingaged him in it, not to be one, &amp; that it was impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for him to be wholly unacquainted with it. He was to have come to me two days afterwards, to give me more
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:98116:21"/>certain intelligences of it, and to know my reſolution, but he was the next day killed in the ſedition you know late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly happened in this City, which has been the cauſe that I could not know any thing more of it. You ought after this adviſe to conſerve the days that are ſo dear to the State.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Poligeſne.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>Theomedes</hi> had no ſooner read over this Letter, but he went and carried it to the King, who was greatly ſurprized to finde the name of <hi>Democrates</hi> in it; but as he could not imagine him to be capable of ſo great a baſeneſs, he would not make him be arreſted, as <hi>Theomedes</hi> demanded, before he had ſent to his houſe who had writ this Letter, to ſee if no ways were to be found out whereby to get ſome further diſcoveries and ſatisfactions: but thoſe who went thither having found him dead,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:98116:22"/>came back without having got any other information, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out having learnt any thing that might deliver them out of the trouble and confuſion into which in all probability this Letter was likely to caſt I know not how many.</p>
            <p>This could not be kept ſo ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret; but that <hi>Democrates</hi> who had great friends, was advertiſed of it; but as he knew himſelf in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent, and did not think the King had any ſuſpicion to his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advantage, nor gave any credit to the Impoſture, he would not follow the advice of thoſe who councell'd him to fly.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seſtianes,</hi> who was the Author of this conſpiracy, having con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſedly learnt this news, and fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that <hi>Democrates,</hi> who as it was reported, knew the name of the chief of the conſpiracy, would diſcover him, came to ſee him
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:98116:22"/>without examining well what he did, as moſt guilty perſons do, who loſe their Judgement by the fear they have upon them, and <q>told him, that he had heard he would accuſe him; but that thoſe who might have told him he was guilty (in caſe he had been told ſo) accuſed him un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtly, and their ſuſpicions were not grounded any otherwiſe then in that they knew the Prince <hi>Theomedes</hi> was his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and hated him mortally, which made them believe that, to be delivered of ſo powerfull and redoubted an Enemy, and who was very prejudicial to him at Court, he had reſolved to be his death.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>This Diſcourſe much ſurpriz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Democrates,</hi> he told <hi>Seſtianes</hi> that he acquainted him with things he had never heard of, that he did not believe he could
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:98116:23"/>ceive ſo horrible a thought, and ſo contrary his glory, and that never to having known the Authors, nor the complices of this conſpiracy, nor ſo much indeed as that they had conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red it, he nere thought of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſing him, nor any other:</q> thoſe words in ſome meaſure diſſipated <hi>Seſtianes</hi>'s fear, and kept him from flying, as he had propoſed to himſelf. He went after he had quitted <hi>Democrates,</hi> to find out his companions in this conſpiracy, and bid them not be allarm'd, whatſoever they might hear re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported, for he was ſure there was no body knew any thing.</p>
            <p>Whilſt things went on thus, they reſolved to arreſt <hi>Democrates,</hi> to oblige him to tell what he knew of this conſpiracy. This unfortunate Heroe learnt this news without appearing in the leaſt allarmed at it, and indeed
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:98116:23"/>without any change of counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance; and as he relyed much upon his innocence, he went to addreſs himſelf to his Prince as he was wont to do, which cauſed him to have the honour of being arreſted in the Kings Palace, and conducted to Priſon by thoſe Guards. He was kept there two days without having any thing ſaid to him, and on the third he was interrogated, but to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, this unhappy Innocent not being able to diſcover what he did not know; they ſhewed him af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards <hi>Poligeſne's</hi> Letter, to ſee whither that would not ſurprize him, and make ſome motion in his face. But he without ſeeming any whit aſtoniſhed, anſwer'd thoſe that ſhewed it him, that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Poligeſne</hi> was an impoſtor, or that he who had a mind to have ſeduced him was one, and as theſe Judges could not get any
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:98116:24"/>other anſwer from him, they went their way, and related no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to the King and Prince <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>omedes,</hi> but only the reſolution of <hi>Democrates.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When thoſe who came to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrogate him were gone, he made reflections upon the Letter they had ſhowed him, by which he underſtood that the Author of the conſpiracy was of his acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and one of his friends: he run over in his mind all thoſe he knew, to ſee if among his friends there was any he could think ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of this baſeneſs, and upon whom he might faſten his ſuſpici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; but not having found any, he remembred what <hi>Seſtianes</hi> had come and told him ſome time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he was taken priſoner, and immediately ſuſpected part of the truth, which greatly troubled him, and gave him cruel inquie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes; for if on one ſide he was
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:98116:24"/>almoſt ready to diſpair to have any reaſon to ſuſpect the father of his Miſtreſs of an action ſo foul and ſo unworthy a man of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour; on the other ſide he thought himſelf obliged to tell all he knew, and was perſwaded that it was to make himſelf a criminal, and to wound his honour to keep it undiſcovered; yet after he had conſulted with himſelf what he ſhould do, he ſaw very well that he ought not to accuſe a man of the quality of <hi>Seſtianes</hi> without any proofs, and upon a ſimple conjecture, and that if the evil treatments he had received from the Prince <hi>Theomedes</hi> made his Enemies believe it was he who had conſpired againſt him, it was a motive ſtrong enough to make his friends believe that he was ſuſpected unjuſtly, and that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out knowing the truth, would be to draw conſequences to his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advantage,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:98116:25"/>abſolutely contrary to his glory and injurious to his reputation; wherefore, after he had well conſulted prudence, to ſee what he had beſt do, it gave him only the advice to be ſilent, and not to ſpeak of what it was impoſſible for him to prove, and that which might undoubtedly make him loſe the heart of his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs: yet poſſibly had he heark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned leſſe to the Counſels of pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and had ſaid all he knew, that <hi>Seſtianes</hi> aſtoniſhed, confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and ſurpriſed, as ordinarily moſt criminals are, when they ſee they are diſcovered, would not ſo well have known how to hide his ſurpriſe and trouble, and that his countenance would have diſcovered his crime, but as he had no proofs, it might be not only to run the hazard of loſing the heart of his Miſtreſs, but alſo be in danger to be looked up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:98116:25"/>as an Impoſtor, for uttering that he could not make out: not but that if <hi>Democrates</hi> had been happy, fortune might have made him proſperous in acting after this manner, but as he propoſed to himſelf that he would follow prudence in all things, and not put any thing to hazard, he ought not to undertake that which might be in the leaſt peril<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous.</p>
            <p>In the mean time whilſt that this criminal without a crime, or rather this innocent victim of misfortune, gave himſelf up ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to his inquietude, and ſought out means to get rid of the doubt that was upon his ſpirit, <hi>Seſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes</hi> on his part was in a fear and trouble very difficult to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt. Sometimes he thought <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mocrates</hi> knew his crime, and that the Love he bore his Daughter kept him from ſpeaking of it,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:98116:26"/>ſometimes he fancied he knew nothing of it, and then again he was perſwaded, that he could not be very long Maſter of his ſecret, but would be conſtrain'd to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare it. His mind, being toſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout with all theſe different thoughts, ſucceſſively gave up it ſelf to fear, grief, torment, and hope, without ever getting it diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſeſt of thoſe wracking Inquie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes, no, not in thoſe very mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments wherein he flattered him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf that <hi>Democrates</hi> knew not any thing, or if he had acquainted him with all, his love would have kept him from making any diſcovery.</p>
            <p>Though <hi>Seſtianes</hi> was ſtill in fear, and his diſquiets were great, and though the troubles and cares of <hi>Democrates</hi> were much more ſmart and pungent, and his griefs by far more ſenſible, yet all thoſe torments came not
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:98116:26"/>near the cruel diſpleaſures that <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiana</hi> reſented, and as glory was a thouſand times more dear to her then her life, and love; it was only deſpite that cauſed all her ſighs, ſhe was more deeply touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at <hi>Democrates</hi>'s being impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, becauſe ſhe had loved him, then becauſe ſhe did love him, and ſhe had a moſt unexpreſſable regret that ſhe had ſuffered a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to get her eſteem and tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs whom ſhe Judg'd unworthy of it, and whom ſhe thought was guilty of the moſt ſhamefull and horrid baſeneſs in the world. This generous Perſon did not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble thoſe who cannot hate the objects they have loved, and who cannot ſee the crimes that Lovers do commit after they have once known how to gain their hearts, but with the eyes of their love; that is to ſay, only to excuſe them, ſhe looked not upon the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:98116:27"/>pretended crime of <hi>Democrates</hi> with any other eyes then thoſe of her choller, and only aim'd to be reveng'd both of him, and of her ſelf, for that he had been able to conſtrain her Love; and to make her declare to him the weakneſs of her heart in bearing him ſo ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent an affection: wherefore ſhe took up a reſolution never to marry him, although he ſhould get out of priſon, and be perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reſtored into the Kings favour, unleſs ſhe ſhould be fully purg'd of that injurious ſuſpition with which his reputation had been ſullied.</p>
            <p>Whilſt <hi>Seſtiana</hi> gave up her ſelf wholly to her deſpite, <hi>Democrates</hi> was ſeveral times interrogated; but he ſtill ſhew'd an equal aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and reſolution, and the Prince <hi>Theomedes</hi> not doubting but that he had ſome ſecret Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, took ſo great a care over
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:98116:27"/>himſelf, that thoſe who had a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign to take away his life, could not finde any favourable opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to put their purpoſe in execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>The Impriſonment of <hi>Democra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,</hi> who could not be thought guilty of a crime ſo unworthy of him, and ſo contrary to the great reputation he had acquired, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly troubled ſeveral of his friends: and, above them all, <hi>Anaxander,</hi> who was a ſtranger of an Illuſtrious Family, and whoſe Name is known through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a good part of <hi>Europe.</hi> They had made ſome Voyages toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and had contracted ſo great a friendſhip, that I know not how to expreſs it, but in ſaying, that all the Hiſtories have ſaid of the moſt ſtrongeſt friendſhips in the world cannot equal that which was between them. It had been already a good while that this
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:98116:28"/>ſtranger had deſigned to go back into his own Country, and his departure had not been retarded, but through the great affection he bore to <hi>Democrates,</hi> whom he could not then tell how to leave. But yet now he did reſolve to go, ſeeing his friend in priſon; but it was only for his ſervice, as you will finde in the ſequel.</p>
            <p>This generous and faithfull friend made his departure with all the precipitation he could, and went out of the Kingdome with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out taking his leave of any perſon, and even without ſaluting the King, to whom he was very well known; becauſe all theſe things he thought might be advantagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to him, in the deſigne he had to ſerve his friend, and that he might derive from thence ſuch conſequences, as ſhould be capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to get that to be believed which he had a mind to perſwade.</p>
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:98116:28"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Democrate</hi>'s impriſonment be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to be the publick diſcourſe, both among the great ones, and the common people. All Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments were divided, and there were different thoughts about this action according to the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent inclinations of perſons. Some ſpoke of him as a Notorious Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal, others maintain'd his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocence, and there were ſome that could not tell how to think him either one way or other, and knew not what they had beſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, the King himſelf, and the Prince <hi>Theomedes</hi> began to find themſelves under no ſmall trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and confuſion; whilſt <hi>Demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates,</hi> though the only perſon that was accuſed, and a priſoner, injoy'd a greater tranquillity then any of e'm, and felt his Soul as ſerene and calm as ever.</p>
            <p>Matters were in this poſture, that is to ſay, no more advanced
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:98116:29"/>then they were the firſt day of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mocrates</hi>'s being taken priſoner, when <hi>Anaxander,</hi> who was at laſt gone out of the Kingdome, in which his friend was unjuſtly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed, writ to the King this Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which, if you pleaſe, you may peruſe.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>To the KING.</head>
                  <p>I Thought my ſelf obliged to acquaint your Majeſty, not to let an Innocent perriſh, that I am the Author of that conſpiracy you have heard of, which threatens the life of Prince <hi>Theome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des,</hi> and that the friendſhip which is between <hi>Democrates</hi> and me, hath made ſome of the conſpiratours be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that I might have diſcovered to him the deſigne I had againſt the life of that Prince; but I too much loved that dear and generous friend, to ingage him in it. Yet poſſibly I had
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:98116:29"/>done it, if he had not been your ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject; but his crime had been too great to ſet upon the Relations of a King, from whom he had received ſo many ſignal favours, this reaſon oblig'd me to be carefull of his glory, and not to put him into the unworthy, and cruel neceſſity of betraying, either his King, or his friend. Such an acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment will no doubt ſurpriſe you; but my crime is ſo glorious, that I hope time will diſcover that only the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous can blacken themſelves with the like ſin, and that how criminal ſoever I declare my ſelf to be, poſterity will not reproach my glory. As I ſhould be troubled that Prince <hi>Thoemedes</hi> ſhould loſe his life upon any other ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject then that for which I had reſolved to ſacrifice him, I would inform him that there are ſome of your ſubjects who conſpire againſt him, though I cannot tell by whom they are ingaged to it, nor what their motives is that thruſt them on.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Anaxander.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:98116:30"/>
            <p>As <hi>Anaxander</hi> was indowed both with a great preſence of wit, and command of prudence; and what had happened, concluded him from doubting that Prince <hi>Theomedes</hi> had ſecret Enemies, and that they did conſpire againſt him, ſhe gave him that informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that ſo the confeſſion of a crime which he had not commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, ſhould not make the guilty believe that they were in any ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and likewiſe that this Prince ſhould not expoſe himſelf to their fury.</p>
            <p>I will leave you to Judge of the Kings ſurpriſe, and of the aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of Prince <hi>Theomedes,</hi> as ſoon as they had red <hi>Anaxanders</hi> Letter. They were along time, both of them, without knowing either what they ought to do, or even believe: but at laſt the King, who had not yet ſtifled in his breaſt all the ſentiments of eſteem
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:98116:30"/>he had formerly had for <hi>Democra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,</hi> was of opinion that he might believe that Letter, and that which confirm'd it in his thoughts was the remembrance of that precipitation that <hi>Anaxan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> had made to be gone, and that he ſeem'd to glory in his crime, in ſaying, <hi>that poſterity would not reproach his glory,</hi> and the agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment he found of this Letter to that of <hi>Poligeſne's,</hi> who had writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten that he was not aſſured of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mocrates</hi>'s being joined in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy; but that he believ'd he might poſſibly know of it, becauſe one of his friends was the Author of it.</p>
            <p>As we live in an age where in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention reigns, and where expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience diſcovers dayly that it is not in the power of Kings to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a priſoner from knowing all that paſſes, either for, or againſt him, the friends of <hi>Democrates</hi>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:98116:31"/>ſoon got him to be informed of all that <hi>Anaxander</hi> had writ in his favour; they alſo got convey'd a copy of the Letter he had ſent to the King, in his juſtification. This Letter gave our illuſtrious priſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er as great a trouble and intangle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as it had done the King, and Prince <hi>Theomedes;</hi> he could not perſwade himſelf that a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſo generous, and the very bottom of whoſe ſoul he thought he knew, could be capable of ſuch a crime, and the more he conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered him either as innocent, or guilty, he was reſolv'd to ſave his life, the more that generoſity made him doubt that he was guilty.</p>
            <p>He had not been many mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in that reflection, but he quited it to fix upon another. <q>If <hi>Anaxander</hi> ſaid he, in himſelf, was innocent, he would have found out ſome way to let me
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:98116:31"/>underſtand that he did not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe himſelf, but to ſave me my honour, and perhaps my life; and would not have expos'd me to the hard Neceſſity of doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his Innocence, in a time, wherein he would poſſibly have divulged mine at the expence of his glory.</q> He was a long while in this cruel uncertainty, but at laſt whatever ground he had to doubt, he could not be perſwaded that ſo perfect a friend could poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly be guilty.</p>
            <p>Though <hi>Democrates</hi> had a deal of prudence, and a very piercing wit, he had his imagination fill'd with too many different thoughts, to preſent at once before him, the prudence which <hi>Anaxander</hi> had made uſe of in this emergency. For that generous friend had not a mind, for ſeveral conſiderable reaſons, to let him know the truth of what he writ to the King,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:98116:32"/>he apprehended that he ſhould not finde out a perſon that would be faithful enough to acquaint him with it <hi>viva voce,</hi> or if he ſhould write to him, there might be a great deal of difficulty to get that Letter come ſafe into his hands without any ſurpriſe. But yet theſe were not the principal reaſons which obliged him not to diſcover to <hi>Democrates,</hi> that he was innocent, and only did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare himſelf the contrary to ſerve him, he had a more powerful rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon then all thoſe, and as he knew the generoſity of that il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrious unfortunate man, he did apprehend, that if he did know the truth he would diſcover it, and avow that his friend did only render himſelf criminal to ſerve him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seſtianes</hi> learn'd all that paſs'd, but yet theſe Intelligences could not diſſipate his fears, and ſmooth
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:98116:32"/>his breaſt into a calm, he knew very well that that had not alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the ſtate of things, he ſaw well that if <hi>Democrates</hi> knew he was a criminal, it was ſtill in his power to declare him ſo, and as he was the Author of the conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy, he knew better then any perſon that <hi>Anaxander</hi> could not make himſelf guilty but out of ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neroſity, and to ſave his friend; and he alſo did much doubt of the reaſons which had induc'd him to give that advice, that he had put at the end of his Letter to the Prince <hi>Theomedes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The King, who as I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready told you, began to retrive his eſteem for our Heroe, and who was of opinion that <hi>Anaxan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> Letter might be relied upon, after he had made <hi>Theomedes</hi> to conſent to it, who was the moſt intereſſed in this affair, declared that <hi>Democrates</hi> was innocent, and
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:98116:33"/>gave order he ſhould be let out of priſon.</p>
            <p>This generous unfortunate per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon was no ſooner ſet at liberty, but he went to throw himſelf at the King's feet. <q>I know <hi>Seignior,</hi> ſaid he to him, how dear the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty which I now receive, has coſt the glory of the moſt perfect friend that ever was: that too o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliging <hi>Anaxander</hi> has not made himſelf guilty but to make me innocent, all his crime is my unhappineſs he has thought he ought to give me at the expence of his reputation, thoſe illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous &amp; almoſt incredible marks of his frendſhip, but too diſadvanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious for himſelf; ſince they make him loſe the eſteem he had ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired among men: I will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume my ſetters to render him back his glory and his inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, mine will be powerfull enough to free me from 'em, or if
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:98116:33"/>in ſpight of all its power I am conſtrain'd to periſh, I ſhall not have the ſenſible and cruell diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure of living, and of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my ſelf the cauſe of a crime which will be unjuſtly imputed to the moſt virtuous of all men. You deſerve, replied the King to him, amaz'd at this diſcourſe, to have chains put on you far more heavy then thoſe you now have quitted, not ſo much for the crime of which you are poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly too juſtly ſuſpected, as for the trouble and confuſion you endeavour to throw into the breaſt of a King, who does all he can to defend you from thoſe perils you are threatned with: I cannot ſecure you from them with juſtice, but in finding an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other guilty who juſtifies you; and yet when I have found him you implore your Rhetorick to perſwade me that he is inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:98116:34"/>and do all you can to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy what I have been hitherto doing for you. Ceaſe, ungrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, your oppoſition to my boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and if you will not do it, becauſe I deſire it, do it then ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther out of pity to your ſelf, or from the obedience you owe me, and do not give me the regret of making him periſh, who has been heretofore honoured with my Confidence: Though you ſhould believe <hi>Anaxander</hi> is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent, yet receive the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of that friendſhip he gives you, and do not publiſh that he is not guilty, but leave it to time to juſtifie him; it renders juſtice to all the world, it does not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer it ſelf to be corrupted but of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes brings to light the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocence of thoſe who have been thought culpable, and the crimes of thoſe who paſs not only for innocent but likewiſe for moſt
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:98116:34"/>virtuous. Think upon what I ſay, and take you heed of pulling down my anger upon you, which ſhould be ſo much the more vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent as you ſhall have forc'd it to break out.</q>
            </p>
            <p>The King ſaid no more to him but left <hi>Democrates</hi> in an inquie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude and perplexity, from which he found it very painful to relieve himſelf.</p>
            <p>He was hardly got to his own houſe, but he complain'd of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, which had too dearly ſold him the liberty he had then ſo lately received; inſomuch that he did as earneſtly deſire as ever he had done, to be ſent back into the priſon from which he was but newly delivered; and alſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain'd of the Kings favours to him, which he then found too cruel: <q>What, ſaid he to himſelf, in reflecting upon what that Prince had told him, ought I to
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:98116:35"/>ſuffer ſo faithful a friend as <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naxaender,</hi> who gives me ſuch powerfull and generous marks of his friendſhip, to loſe for my ſake the reputation he has got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the world? ought I to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer his name to be diſhonoured, and poſterity to doubt of his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocence? but on the other ſide, ought I to oppoſe the commands of my Prince? ought I to deny him that which he requires of me? ought I to deſpiſe his boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and cauſe a moment of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quietude to a King who hath ſo much loved me, and from whom I have received ſo many ſignal benefits? no, no, I owe too much to that Royal Benefactor, I cannot without a crime reſiſt his commands; but though he ſhould have never beſtowed any favour on me, he is my Prince, and I am his ſubject, and in that quality I owe him all. Love, and
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:98116:35"/>friendſhip ought to give place to duty, Subjects owe all to their Prince, and we owe him obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence preferably to thoſe who brought us into the world.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Democrates</hi> thus entertain'd his thoughts, when <hi>Seſtianes</hi> came to viſit him, to congratulate him for the good fortune of being ſet at liberty. After he had payd his compliments, <hi>Democrates</hi> told him what had taken up his imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on before his arrival, and the ſcruple he had to ſuffer it to be thought that ſo perfect a friend as <hi>Anaxander</hi> was ſhould be capable of the moſt baſe and infamous of all crimes, and the moſt unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy the title of a gallant or gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous man.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seſtianes,</hi> who fearing leſt he ſhould be diſcovered, had wiſhed with all his ſoul they had never ſpoke of this conſpiracy, and that <hi>Anaxander</hi> who was abſent had
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:98116:36"/>ſtill been thought culpable, anſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wered him, that if that friend was criminal, he ought not to have that ſcruple, and that he was extreamly too blame to conſerve it if he was not. <q>The generous, added he, always receive a great deal of renown from their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous actions; <hi>Anaxander,</hi> in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what he has done for you, hath labour'd more for his own glory then for yours; that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſſed generous perſon in ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving your life, and in reſtoring the honour of it to you, puts you but in the condition you were before ſuſpected; but what does he not do for himſelf? ſince by it he obtains the immortal &amp; glorious happineſs of paſſing in the ages to come for a grand ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of friendſhip, ſince he will have the glory of having been the moſt generous man in the world, and of having done the
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:98116:36"/>moſt remarkable action that ever was, and which will make his memory live, and poſterity ſpeak of him with admiration and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logies: do not you put ſo many obſtacles, purſued he, to ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many glorious advantages that he would preſently purchaſe at the expence of a little honour, which he will only loſe for a time, and which will be reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to him with much more lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtre then it will be loſt with ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominy; this is the fruit he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects from the ſervice that he ſhall have rendred you, and this is that which he will gain in ſerving of you, if you do not op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it: Do not ſpeak any more of crime or guilty, and let the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance thereof for a time lie dead, ſince that otherwiſe <hi>Anax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> could not acquire the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry he aims at from ſo generous an action, and that it would be ſaid
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:98116:37"/>he is of intelligence with you, and that you are reſolved to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that to him which he lends you in the ſame time he gives it to you. <hi>Democrates</hi> anſwered <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianes,</hi> that all thoſe reaſons could not ſatisfie the ſcruple he had in him, that poſterity did not always do juſtice, and that very often it was misinform'd of the truth; that it made him al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt deſpair to ſee the glory of his friend hazarded for ever, whilſt that the truly guilty liv'd in ſafety;</q> he brought out thoſe words with an air that made <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianes</hi> believe he intended them to be ſpoke to him, which was the cauſe that he did what we ſhall tell you in the ſucceſſion of this Hiſtory.</p>
            <p>As ſoon as <hi>Seſtianes</hi> was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted, <hi>Democrates</hi> went to ſee his Miſtreſſe, whom he found all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone; he went to caſt himſelf
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:98116:37"/>down at her feet, but <hi>Seſtiana</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented his doing it, and told him with a great deal of fierceneſſe and ſcorn, that after what had befell him ſhe could no longer hearken to his ſighs without wounding her glory, nor ſuffer a criminal to entertain her with his paſſion. Ah! Madam, replied <hi>Democrates</hi> to her, with an air extream full <q>of reſpect, and as ſorrowful as paſſionate, if all the wretched are Criminals, I avow to you I am the moſt guilty of all men, ſince I am the moſt unfortunate, but yet not ſo much, for having been unjuſtly ſuſpected of the moſt ſhameful baſeneſſe imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, but becauſe I have no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger the glorious advantage of being beloved by the moſt beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful and moſt equitable perſon in the earth: Since you believe me equitable, anſwered <hi>Seſtiana</hi> to him, you ought not to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:98116:38"/>of me. I ſee plainly, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd that unfortunate Lover to her, that though to this preſent I always thought my ſelf to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent, that I had never brought any reproach to my glory, and that alſo now, I do not know my crime, yet I muſt needs be a grand Criminal, ſince you doubt of my Innocence. I doubt it with Juſtice, reported to him the provoked fair one, and if what <hi>Anaxander</hi> has written in your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour was ſufficient to get you out of priſon, and to reſtore you your life, it is not ſufficient to render you your honour, nor is it enough to make me believe that I ſhould not love in you a man blaſted with a moſt hatefull crime; it is not enough to hinder me from doubting your inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, and it is not enough for my ſatisfaction, for my repoſe, and for my glory. Ah! where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:98116:38"/>have I ever ſeen you? wherefore have you diſcovered your flames to me? wherefore have I loved you? wherefore have you been able to conſtrain me in ſpight of my ſelf to ſhow you my tendereſt affections; wherefore have you put me in a capacity of regretting all my life the love I have born you? and wherefore ſhall I ſpeak it? yes, to puniſh you for your crime, to puniſh you for having known how to conſtrain me to confeſs my Love to you, and to make you ſuffer if you ſtill love me; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore—but whence is it that my heart cannot ſpeak it without ſighing, wherefore baſe man? wherefore notwithſtanding all my deſpite, have I ſtill more love for you then I ought to have. Though I read in your counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance that this diſcourſe is not diſpleaſing to you, purſued ſhe,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:98116:39"/>with eyes inflamed with diſpite, with love, and rage, and that you meet with nothing in it to puniſh you, yet know, that this new confeſſion of my flame ought to make you ſuffer more then you imagine, if you loved me truly; ſince there is nothing in the world can oblige me to give you my hand, before your innocence be ſo fully juſtifyed, that I ſhall have no further room to doubt of it; for in a word, continued ſhe, though you be pardoned, yet you are not ſufficiently juſtifyed. When one has once loſt one's ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, it is not ſo eaſily recovered, and there is need of more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincing proofs then what a friend writes, who would gladly ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice his glory to the friendſhip he has for you, and who poſſibly would ſpeak otherwiſe, if he once ſaw himſelf charged with fetters.</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="75" facs="tcp:98116:39"/>
            <p>This diſcourſe gave <hi>Democrates</hi> both a ſenſible affliction, and as ſenſible a joy; for if on the one ſide he was even raviſhed to learn that <hi>Seſtiana</hi> had loved him always, and to ſee that notwithſtanding all her deſpite ſhe had not the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to conceal her love from him; on the other ſide he reſented a moſt incredible grief to ſee him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf not in a condition to poſſeſſe her, nor that he knew any ways in the world how to juſtine his innocence ſo fully, that it might be impoſſible for his fair and beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful Miſtreſs to be able to doubt of it. Theſe thoughts for ſome time took up his minde, and oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned him for ſome moments not to anſwer her, but at laſt he broke off his ſilence, and ſaid to her, <q>I do not know any thing, Madam, that can better prove my innocence to you, and that can better make it known to all the
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:98116:40"/>world, then the paſſion I have for you, and which I have been ſo hardy as to declare to you A heart that had found it ſelf cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable, would not have had a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient aſſurance to give you the marks of his flame, and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of you the permiſſion and honour to ſigh for you, it would not have dared to adde this crime to that which it would have been ſullied with, and it would have apprehended that your wit and your eyes which penetrate all things, and which have a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular power of diſcerning, would quickly have found out both its crime and its moſt ſecret ſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Do not endeavour, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupted <hi>Seſtiana,</hi> to ſeduce my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>pite by this flattering diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, and if you will oblige me, let me alone to enjoy it till ſuch time that I ſhall be no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger able to doubt of your inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence.
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:98116:40"/>I muſt then, replied <hi>Democrates</hi> to her, wait (if ſo be I can do it without expiring) till fortune which has rendered me guilty, makes a diſcovery of my inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence; poſſibly it will labour my juſtification, when I ſhall leaſt think of it, in the ſame manner as it has laboured to eclipſe my glory, when I as little ſuſpected it. As this inconſtant Deity of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten makes perſons guilty, that ſo ſhe may divert her ſelf with the trouble and confuſion into which ſhe caſts them, ſhe is alſo pleaſed to reſtore them their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocence, when they believe their virtue ſhall never be known, and when they diſpair to ſee them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves again in the ſame degree of honour as they were before they had the unhappineſs to be attacked by that flitting good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. This time will come, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, and you will know then
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:98116:41"/>that I am not altogether unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of the Love you bear me. Ah! why is not this time come alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, cried <hi>Seſtiana</hi> to her ſelf, do not you imagine, replied ſhe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately, that Love makes me ſpeak in this manner, it is my glory only that takes up all my thoughts, and all that is capable of ſecuring it, ſo ſenſibly touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es me, that none ought to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire I ſhow ſo much of ardour, when there is ſomething told me that may ſerve either to re-eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh it, or bring an acceſſion to it. But, Madam, did <hi>Democrates</hi> anſwer her, if by the juſtifying of my innocence, I could ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der you the glory which you have loſt, becauſe you have lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved me, ſhall not your love be ſatisfied, and ſhall not this juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication be alſo as ſenſible to it as to your glory? Be you the judge of it, repeated <hi>Seſtiana</hi> to him,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:98116:41"/>the tenderneſs you know I have for you, and do not demand any thing more of me.</q> They were yet ſome time together, during which <hi>Democrates</hi> knew, that if that fair one had any great love for him, ſhe had yet a greater aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendent over her ſpirit, and that it would be impoſſible for him to obtain her hand, before he ſhould purge himſelf of the pretended crime with which ſhe thought he might be yet ſuſpected.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Democrates</hi> was ſcarcely gone from <hi>Seſtiana,</hi> but he was think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the means to juſtify himſelf in that manner as the fair one de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded; but the more he was muſing on 'em, the more he found himſelf perplexed, for he began to believe that <hi>Seſtianes</hi> was the true criminal, and the Councel that he had given him, to believe that <hi>Anaxander</hi> was guilty, and to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſh the remembrance of a
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:98116:42"/>crime whereof it was almoſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to diſcover the Author, added to what he had told him juſt before he was taken priſoner, confirmed him in that thought, and redoubled the inquietude that tormented him. <q>What if I ſhould ſaid he accuſe <hi>Seſtianes?</hi> what if he ſhould confeſs his crime, and by his acknowledgment I ſhould be juſtified? I ſhould then do what <hi>Seſtiana</hi> requires of me, I ſhould likewiſe make a diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of my innocence, and ſatisfie her glory; but alſo, as that would cauſe me to do more than ſhe demands, I ſhould, in find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out the means of making my ſelf be beloved, finde out thoſe of making my ſelf be hated at the ſame time. I ſhould, in finding out the means of obtaining her hand, find out thoſe of making her refuſe to give it me, and to conclude, I ſhould in finding out
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:98116:42"/>the means of juſtifying my ſelf, finde out thoſe of making my ſelf in her eſteem guilty of a crime much more odious than this is now lie under the imputation of and ſuch are the rigours and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verities of fate which is reſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly determined to follow me, that I cannot do the one without the other, not paſs for innocent be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the object to whom I would juſtify my ſelf, without paſſing at the ſame time in her thoughts for ungratefull, cruel, and for much more guilty than I do ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to her at preſent.</q> After that this afflicted Lover had been for ſome time entertaining him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with theſe ſad and lamentable thoughts, and had made all theſe things be run over in his imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, he was immovable like a ſtatue for a good conſiderable time, and ſtood as it were ſo buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in his grief, that very ſcarcely
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:98116:43"/>did he give any ſign of life: when he was a little come out of that trouble which the exceſs of his grief had caſt him into, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thought himſelf on a ſudden, that he had found out the ſecret of get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of the incertainty and trouble in which he was. <q>I muſt, ſaid he to himſelf, declare to <hi>Seſtiana</hi> all I know, and diſcover to her all the reaſons that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade me, to believe her father is the Author of the crime of which I am ſuſpected, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of her that ſhe will marry me by way of recompence, for having ſo faithfully kept the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret, and to oblige me to keep it ſtill, and I hope that the ſilence I have obſerved for her ſake, and the fear ſhe will have of my breaking it, will cauſe her not to refuſe giving me her hand, leaſt ſhe appear ungratefull towards her Father and me.</q> He had
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:98116:43"/>hardly remain'd a moment in theſe remarkable &amp; flattering thoughts, but he quitted them to let himſelf be hurried away by others. <q>To act in this manner, ſaid he, would be to hazard too much, if <hi>Seſtiana</hi> ſhould not give any be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief to my diſcourſe, ſhe would be obliged to have for me an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincible hatred, and far from obtaining it by this way, I ſhould for ever loſe the place I poſſeſs in her heart: I ought therefore to act with prudence, it is too fair a virtue to loſe, it will fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh me with other means to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the end of my deſires; and as I am ſure of the tender affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of that divine beauty which cauſes all my pains, I ought to hope that ſhe will have pitty of my torments, and that time, my ſervices, my reſpects, and my innocence will make her at laſt reſolve to marry me.</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="84" facs="tcp:98116:44"/>
            <p>Theſe were the flattering hopes wherewith <hi>Democrates</hi> buoy'd up himſelf, and the deference he had for the Councells that prudence gave him; but it ought not to be wondered at, he never remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred that it had always been a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, he forgot the miſeries that it had cauſed him, as ſoon as ever the danger or the miſchief was paſt, and though it had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways proved treacherous to him, he would nevertheleſs rely upon it, and could not reſolve to aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don it.</p>
            <p>A little while after he returned to <hi>Seſtiana,</hi> whom he found as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincible as before, and who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated to him only the ſame things that ſhe had already ſaid; which gave him ſuch a cruel vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation and deſpite, that he went to tell her Father how obſtinately ſhe refuſed to marry him, and withall to deſire him that he
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:98116:44"/>would conſider his promiſe to him, and to ſpeak to <hi>Seſtiana</hi> in his favour. <hi>Seſtianes</hi> who had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to ruin <hi>Democrates,</hi> and who notwithſtanding all the love this paſſionate Gallant had for his Daughter, did not think himſelf ſecure; becauſe he perſwaded himſelf that he might very well betray a Father-in Law, to reeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh the glory of a friend, to whom he was ſo greatly obliged; received him outwardly with the greateſt joy imaginable, for he had reſolved to be very civil to him untill he ſhould finde a fit opportunity to work his abſolute ruin, he promiſed him to imploy with his Daughter all the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of a Father, and declared to him that he ſhould be ſenſible how great his ſatisfaction was in it by the earneſtneſs of his indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to conclude their Marriage. <hi>Democrates</hi> conjured him not to
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:98116:45"/>employ all his authority, and not to be inraged againſt the object of his moſt dear and tender de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, and told him, that the love he had for <hi>Seſtiana</hi> was too full of reſpect to deſire ſhe ſhould be any whit provoked, or to have her o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliged to do any thing with vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence. <hi>Seſtianes</hi> made anſwer to him, that he was exceeding glad to finde in him thoſe ſentiments, and that he would manage things in ſuch a manner as that both ſhould be ſatisfyed.</p>
            <p>After that <hi>Democrates</hi> had given him a thouſand thanks, and had conjured him to be as good as his word, he took his leave of him; but <hi>Sestianes</hi> to continue the part of a diſſembling impoſtor and trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, that he had accuſtomed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to act; inſtead of what he had promiſed to do for him, bid his daughter always to treat him in that manner ſhe had done ſince
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:98116:45"/>that he was got out of priſon, and forbad her to let him know it was by his order that ſhe treated him ſo. As that generous perſon thought her Father acted by the fame motives as ſhe did, this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe did not give her any trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and ſhe preſently replied to him, that ſhe would obey him ſo much the more willingly, as that he commanded nothing of her but what ſhe had already reſolved to do. A little while after there was preſented to <hi>Seſtiana</hi> a match more conſiderable by far then <hi>Democra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes</hi> was. This blinde Father, whoſe ambition was the only engine that moved him in all his actions, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately bid his Daughter not to reject <hi>Arcas,</hi> (for ſo was this new Lover called) but to keep him up with ſome ſmall hopes, but yet without letting <hi>Democrates</hi> know it was by his command; which cauſed <hi>Seſtiana</hi> to be very much
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:98116:46"/>troubled, and which made her know more certainly that ſhe ſtill bore our Heroe a far greater Love than ever ſhe imagined. Yet <hi>Seſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anes</hi> began to finde himſelf in a ſtrange perplexity, for he durſt not let his Daughter marry <hi>Arcas,</hi> becauſe ſhe was long before pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to <hi>Democrates,</hi> and he was terrible afraid that this affront might provoke him ſo, as to make him ſpeak all that he thought he knew, ſooner then he would have done: and on the other ſide, he would not give her to <hi>Democrates;</hi> becauſe he was only ſearching for a favourable occaſion to ruin him.</p>
            <p>During this inquietude of his, our Heroe who relied upon his word, and upon the Love which <hi>Seſtiana</hi> had not been able to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal from him, began to have his minde now more at eaſe, and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in him; without ever in the leaſt forſeeing the new misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:98116:46"/>with which he was threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. After he had taken order about his Love, he was contriving ſome means not to paſs for un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratefull towards <hi>Anaxander,</hi> whom he always thought inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent of the crime of which he had accuſed himſelf; but not preciſely knowing the place where he was, and not being willing to write to him by ordinary ways, he gave a letter to one of his own Servants, and ſent him to look him out, where he imagined he was moſt likely to be, and as he did not doubt of the fidelity of this Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, from whom he had never any thing of a ſecret, and that he would not have <hi>Anaxander</hi> believe he had hazarded his reputation to ſave a guilty perſon, he ordered him to aſſure him from his own mouth that he was innocent, and to tell him, to prove the truth of it to him, that he thought that
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:98116:47"/>
               <hi>Seſtianes</hi> was really guilty, and the authour of that conſpiracy; but that he had no minde to accuſe him, becauſe of the love he bore to his daughter, and not being willing to truſt all this to paper, he only writ five or ſix lines to this moſt dear friend, to give him proofs of his health, and to make him ſee that he enjoyed the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty which he ſo frankly had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured him.</p>
            <p>As we live in an age where a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret is no longer a virtue, and the things that we would keep the moſt private and concealed, are in a ſhort time known to thoſe from whom we moſt deſire to have them kept a miſtery, it ſeems <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mocrates</hi> was not long without ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending he had a Rival, and that a favoured one too, not only by the father of his Miſtriſs, but by his Miſtriſs her ſelf; this news was more ſenſible to him, and
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:98116:47"/>touched him deeper then all the outragious cruelties that fortune had till then made him ſuffer; he abandoned himſelf wholly to his grief and rage, he called a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand times <hi>Seſtiana</hi> faithleſs, and <hi>Seſtianes</hi> a traitour, and perfidious, and even doubted ſometimes if he had not beſt tell all that obliged him to believe, that he was the authour of the conſpiracy which had been made againſt <hi>Theomedes;</hi> but as he was too prudent to hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to thoſe thoughts that were conceived in the heats and tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports of a firſt motion, and to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the counſels of choler, he quickly turned from that deſigne to another, <hi>viz.</hi> of going to wait upon <hi>Seſtianes</hi> and his daughter, &amp; to reproach them for their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidiouſneſſe, and their breach of promiſe; but whether they were not within, or elſe that they would not be ſpoke withal by him, it was
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:98116:48"/>impoſſible for him to have a ſight of them.</p>
            <p>If the news of <hi>Arca</hi>'s love had been a very great affliction to <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mocrates, Seſtianes</hi> was quite de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpairing when he underſtood that he had heard of it, becauſe he ſaw himſelf thereby obliged to labour his ruine; for his ambition to ſee his daughter married to <hi>Arcas</hi> (who next to the Princes of the bloud, was one of the firſt of the Kingdom) being joyned to the fear he was in, that <hi>Democrates</hi> would diſcover him one day, and that likewiſe after an affront ſo ſenſible to his flame, he would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare that he was criminall much ſooner then he had or would have done, did powerfully ſollicit him to procure his ruine, in what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſoever it might be; but this new misfortune obliged him to take the ſooneſt opportunity he could to do it in; wherefore from
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:98116:48"/>that day, after he had command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Daughter to treat <hi>Arcas</hi> &amp; <hi>Democrates</hi> with an equal kinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and to endeavour to keep them both to her, until ſuch time that he ſhould make known his choice to her, he went his way to one of his Countrey houſes, with two or three of thoſe that were of the conſpiracy againſt <hi>Theomedes,</hi> that ſo they might contrive a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them the means to execute the deſigne he had projected, and to diſcourſe together freely, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being afraid of any ones over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearing them. They were ſcarce got half a league from the Town, when they perceived a good way off them a man ſet upon by three others; they did what they could to relieve him, but the aſſailants who were theeves, ſeeing them coming up directly to them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took themſelves to flight; but the rage they were in to ſee them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:98116:49"/>ſurpriſed, made them give this perſon whom they had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned to rob, ſeveral wounds, ſo that <hi>Seſtianes</hi> and thoſe with him found the poor miſerable wretch even without life; when they were got up to him, they ſearched him immediately to ſee if they could finde any thing about him which might ſerve to make him known, but they met with nothing ſave a Letter which was directed to <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naxander,</hi> and which was written with <hi>Democrates</hi> his own hand, which made them, after they had anew examined who it might poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly be, to know for certain that it was one of his own ſervants, (for indeed it was he whom <hi>Demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates</hi> had ſent to <hi>Anaxander.</hi>) <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianes</hi> had eaſily got open the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, for as it happened, it had been run through with one of the thruſts that the dead body had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, juſt there where the ſeal
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:98116:49"/>was, ſo that it was in a manner o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen of it ſelf: he read it with a great deal of pleaſure and ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, becauſe it might make the innocence of our Heroe be called again into queſtion, and becauſe he thought that it might ſerve him in the deſigne he had, which cauſed him to give it thoſe to read who were with him, who told him after they had ſeen it, that it would be ſufficient to ſhew it to the King and to Prince <hi>Theomedes,</hi> to get <hi>Democrates</hi> be put into fetters a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, from which he was but new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly releaſed, and to make him be believed that he was guilty. <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianes</hi> who would have had ſurer ways to ruin him, at firſt reſiſted it; but at laſt he reſolved upon it, ſeeing he ſhould not expoſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to any danger in doing ſo, and that he ought not to let ſlip an occaſion that fortune ſeemed to preſent to him expreſly for his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:98116:50"/>and that which yet was a ſtronger inducement to him, was, that if by that means he came not to the end of his hopes, it ſhould be in his power in the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as before, to execute what he had reſolved upon. The matter being thus ſetled, one of the two who had given this counſel, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>called his word a few moneths af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and ſaid, that they had not well weighed what they did, and that <hi>Seſtianes</hi> would be likely to deſtroy himſelf, if he went to put in execution what they had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected together; ſince that <hi>Demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates</hi> ſeeing himſelf accuſed by him whom he knew to be really guilty, would not be able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frain accuſing him in his turn, and to tell all that he knew. That is all that I demand, replied <hi>Seſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,</hi> and that is the true way to ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie my ſelf, and for ever to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive me of the fear that I have of
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:98116:50"/>being diſcovered. When I ſhall have accuſed <hi>Democrates,</hi> and he ſhall accuſe me afterwards, he won't be thought worthy to be believed, nor will any thing he ſhall ſay find any credit, for they will cry out, that he ſpeaks ſo meerly out of rage and matter of revenge, that he would not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe me but only becauſe I have impeach'd him, and if he had known that I had been a criminal, he would not have tarried ſo long before he had accuſed me. All thoſe that would accuſe me after this, let them know my crime, or or know it not, will be look'd upon as Impoſtors, and it will not be hard for me to make it be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved, either that they are friends to <hi>Democrates,</hi> or that they are gained by him; So that that Letter will be doubly profitable to me, for it will both ſerve me a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Democrates,</hi> and againſt
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:98116:51"/>thoſe who ſhall be apt to accuſe me, and it will likewiſe keep off others from having the confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to do it, for fear leaſt I turn the crime upon themſelves.</p>
            <p>This perfidious Man, having confirmed himſelf in this reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſo fitly took his time, that he did not give the King this let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter but in the preſence of Prince <hi>Theomedes,</hi> for fear, that if the Prince had not been there by, the oſteem the King had for <hi>Democra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes</hi> had kept him from making him be arreſted again, and that he had quite ſtifled this proof of his crime.</p>
            <p>The ſucceſs of this baſeneſs an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered the expectation of him who had been guilty of it: the King after he had learnt how this Letter came to be found, and had read it over, could not refrain ſhewing it to Prince <hi>Theomedes;</hi> becauſe that <hi>Seſtianes</hi> in giving it
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:98116:51"/>to him had ſaid out aloud enough to make the Prince know what it was.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Theomedes</hi> having ſeen the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, ſaid without much exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning what he had read, he was ſo highly tranſported with choler, that <hi>Democrates</hi> having himſelf giving undiſputable proofs of his crime, it was very fit and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to have him clapt up again, and that without doubt he would acknowledge then what they could not before get him to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs. The King who thought that demand was juſt and equitable, immediatly gave orders to have him put anew into priſon. He could not but admire as well as <hi>Theomedes</hi> to ſee <hi>Seſtianes</hi> accuſe a man that was ſo neer being his Son in Law; but he anſwered, that he ought to ſacrifice all things to the Royall blood, and that ſince <hi>Democrates</hi> was guilty
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:98116:52"/>of ſo ignominious a crime, he was unworthy to come into his fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that he had loſt all the eſteem he once had for him, and that he would no longer acknowledge him for a man that aſpired to be made happy in the poſſeſſion of his Daughter.</p>
            <p>The unfortunate <hi>Democrates</hi> therefore return'd to his fetters from which he had been but new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly releaſed, but he was not long there before they ſpoke to him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it, for the next day he was ſent for to be interrogated, and to ſee what he had to ſay for the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he had written to <hi>Anaxander</hi> which they ſhewed him; it was contained in theſe words.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="text">
               <body>
                  <pb n="101" facs="tcp:98116:52"/>
                  <head>DEMOCRATES <hi>to the Generous</hi> ANAXANDER.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>TO charge your ſelf with my crime to free me from my fetters, and to oblige me, to ruine the great repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation you have in the world, and the eſteem that your vertue has gained you are ſuch ſignal and valuable favours, as can never be returned; and I muſt acknowledg that I ſhall be obliged to you, not only ſo long as I live, but even after I am dead, ſince you have kept my memory from being ſtained with a crime of which you your ſelf have purged me. I will not ſay any more about it, for I believe you are not ignorant that if nothing can be i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magined capable to requite ſuch an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation, it is impoſſible to find out terms that may be ſufficient to expreſs
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:98116:53"/>it well, wherefore I will content my ſelf to aſſure you that I am ready to pour out all my blood for the generous</hi> Anaxander, <hi>to which I owe both my honour and my life.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>After that <hi>Democrates</hi> had ſeen this Letter, he ſaid without ever altering his countenance, that indeed it was writ with his own hand, and that he did not ſee it could be any ways prejudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial to him, nor did it make it e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident that he was guilty of a crime that had never entered in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his thoughts; his Judges re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied to him that his Letter was contrary to his words, and that he affirmed in it, <hi>that</hi> Anaxander <hi>had charged himſelf with a crime to deliver him from his Fetters, and that he was redevable to him for his life.</hi> They added, that nothing was able to keep them from believing ſuch convincing proofs, and that
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:98116:53"/>he could not deny what he had juſt then affirmed, in confeſſing the Letter they had ſhewn him, and which was adreſſed to <hi>Anax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander,</hi> was of his own hand-wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting. They bid him afterward ſpeak whither he had any thing to ſay that might ſerve for his juſtification. <q>Honour, replied this illuſtrious and generouspri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner to them, which is a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand times more dear to me than my life, obliges me to anſwer you, and if I was not afraid of loſing it in dying, the world ſhould ſee me run with joy to meet my death; ſince nothing but that can deliver me from the infultation of my evil fortune. I will ſay then ſince it is honour, and not the fear of death, that would have me defend my ſelf, that none need to wonder if I writ to <hi>Anaxander,</hi> not as to a cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal, but as to the generouſeſt
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:98116:54"/>perſon upon earth, ſince I never have believed that he was guilty of the crime which he has accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed himſelf of, to deliver me from the danger he ſaw me threatned withal; but am and ſhall be always perſwaded that his generoſity, and the friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip he has teſtified to me, did oblige him to undertake what he has done in my favour. You cannot doubt but that I thought thus as ſoon as I knew he had im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted that Crime to himſelf, when I ſhall tell you, that I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared it to the King, who is a witneſs you cannot refuſe, and whom every body will think, both in duty and juſtice, you ought to believe. Acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing therefore <hi>Anaxander</hi> inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, and that generous friend having declared himſelf guilty, to diſcover to me the greatneſs of his friendſhip, and to free me
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:98116:54"/>from my chains, could I write otherwiſe to him (without de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving to be looked on for it as a criminal) then that he had charged himſelf with my crime in declaring that he was guilty of that which I my ſelf was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed of, ſince that tho he was innocent and I was ſo likewiſe, it is ſtill true that he did take upon himſelf my crime, ſince it was that which I was accuſed of. Ought one afterwards to won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der if I write to him; that <hi>Iowe him both my honour and my life?</hi> was I not equally in danger, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as innocent, or as a crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal? have not I the ſame obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to him alſo both ways? and has he not done as much for me, as if it had been impoſſible to doubt of the crime which was impoſed upon me?</q>
            </p>
            <p>When <hi>Democrates</hi> had ended his diſcourſe, his Judges went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:98116:55"/>very much ſatisfied with his anſwer, and made it viſible both in their eyes, and countenance, that they approved his reaſons. But that did not keep him from complaining of the rigours and injuſtice of his fate, and to ſhew more concern and trouble at his impriſonment then he had done the firſt time he had been taken. <q>What ſaid he to himſelf, ſeeing he was alone, muſt my prudence and my love procure to me ſo ſenſible an affront? muſt I be ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed by him whom I ought to accuſe? and muſt I be in Irons in the room of him whom I ought to have put there before now? tis too much to ſuffer unjuſtly, let us diſcover the proofs we have of the crime of <hi>Seſtianes,</hi> ſo as he has done thoſe he had a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us, and if that cannot ſave us, nor is able to work his ruin, let us have at leaſt the pleaſure
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:98116:55"/>of accuſing him who impeaches us, of making his innocence to be ſuſpected, and of giving him ſome confuſion and trouble as well as he has us. Yes, the lot is caſt for it, let us no longer hearken either to love or pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. But what, replied he im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately, if I have too long ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken their counſels, and if my prudence ruined me, I cannot in this caſe be imprudent, without doing a far greater injury to my ſelf then prudence has ever done me; ſince that having let the time be loſt of accuſing <hi>Seſtianes</hi> I cannot now ſpeak againſt him, without being look'd upon for an impoſtor, and a wicked wretch, and without giving them to think that it is only re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge which makes me do ſo, and that I would not ruin him but becauſe he has been the cauſe that I am now a priſoner. Ah!
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:98116:56"/>prudence, cryed he to himſelf, after he had reflected upon all the misfortunes it had cauſed him, how dear do you coſt me now? wherefore have you hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered me from putting into the letter I writ to <hi>Anaxander,</hi> all that I had a mind he ſhould know, and wherefore have you counſel'd me to have him only know it by the mouth of him I ſent to him? I do ſee very well that you reſolve I ſhall have the unprofitable ſatisfaction not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of having harkned to, but alſo follow'd your counſels in all things that have happened to me of trouble and vexation, and to conſole me in my misfortunes; you would have me impute all to Fate, which has put things to ſuch a paſs that prudence fails in whatſoever it adviſes, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces effects contrary to thoſe it has been wont to do. It is true,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:98116:56"/>ſaid he, going on talking to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in that melancholy way, that ſince I reſolv'd to be govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by prudence in all things, and have learnt to know it, I have perceived that one ought to rely no more upon it then upon for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, &amp; whatſoever it has made one undertake for the beſt, has often proved to be very unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py. It is at preſent ſo ſuſpected, that thoſe who are directed by it as a guide of their actions, and thoſe who never in the leaſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult it, do equally miſtruſt it, &amp; both of them, thinking that eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry body uſes it as a vail to hide other deſigns then what they make to be viſible, apprehend it in another, and are ſo very fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of it, that they are not ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the miſchief it does, but when they are paſt all hopes &amp; opportunity of remedying it.</q>
            </p>
            <p>This Illuſtrious and Eminent
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:98116:57"/>priſoner, who had no other en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment then that which his ſad and troubled thoughts fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed him withal, was three or four days before he knew what to do, either to ſave himſelf, or ruin himſelf; and during this time, he reſented all that love choler, and revenge do make thoſe ſuffer who are labouring under thoſe 3. cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el paſſions. He laid before him the perfidiouſneſs of <hi>Seſtianes,</hi> whom he began to look upon as the moſt deceitful and wicked of all men breathing, and he did whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver he could to ſtifle the love he had for his Daughter, but ſhe had too powerful an aſcendent in his heart, for him to be able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move her from it in ſo ſhort a time, and he made very unprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table attempts about it; for the more he thought on <hi>Seſtiana,</hi> the more her beauty came into his memory, and notwithſtanding all
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:98116:57"/>his reſiſtance, it gave an acceſſion to the love he had for that charm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing &amp; generous perſon, &amp; which he endeavoured to deſtroy with ſo little ſucceſs.</p>
            <p>As this Irreſolute Lover had his thoughts more upon his love, than his impriſonment, and upon the fetters that <hi>Seſtiana</hi> had made him wear, than on thoſe in which his ſuppoſed crime retained him, word was brought him from the King, that his priſon was open, and he might go out when he pleaſed. This news, which he did not at all ſuſpect, ſurpriſed him exceedingly. He thought the right guilty perſons were diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, and went immediately to be informed of it to one of his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations houſes, who had been ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſerviceable to him the former time when he had been a priſoner, and who ſince his laſt misfortune had found a means to let him
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:98116:58"/>know in his priſon, that he would imploy both all his Eſtate, and all his friends to make him fully con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced of the ſhare he took in his intreſts. As <hi>Democrates</hi> was juſt at his houſe, he met him coming out to acquaint him with all that had happened; he told him that his Judges, knowing the eſteem the King had for him, and being ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perſwaded of his Innocence, by the anſwer he had made them, had declared that they believed him Innocent, and ſaid that tho he ſhould have been a Criminal, yet things were in ſuch a poſture that they could not Judge him with any juſtice. He added, that Prince <hi>Theomedes</hi> having been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired by ſeveral perſons of quality whom he named to him, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to his being ſet at liberty, that Prince thought himſelf oblig'd to ſollicite for him, for fear of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to himſelf any more enemies,
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:98116:58"/>in ſeeking, with too great an ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtneſs and reſolution, the ruine of a perſon whoſe crime was not averred, and who poſſibly had never been his enemy. Our Heroe having underſtood all theſe things, went to return his ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgment to the King for all the favours he had ſhown him. He likewiſe thought himſelf ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to go and thank Prince <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>omedes,</hi> which he did after he had been to wait upon the King; and the next day he went to viſit all thoſe that had intereſſed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in his favour; and after all he ſent one of his ſervants where he ſuſpected <hi>Anaxander</hi> to be, to advertiſe him of all that had hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened; but he gave him no let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, for fear leſt fortune which has perſecuted him with as much fury as blindneſs, ſhould invert the proofs of his innocence, to render him guilty.</p>
            <pb n="114" facs="tcp:98116:59"/>
            <p>After he had done all that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther civility or duty exacted from him, he had a great deſire to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer the demands of his love; to give his flame ſome ſatisfaction; and to go and ſee his Miſtriſs; But what <hi>Seſtianes</hi> had done to ruin him, made him ſee ſo much un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthyneſs in that viſit, that he durſt not grant any thing to his love for fear of bringing any ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh to his glory. Never did any Lover ſee himſelf in a greater and more cruel perplexity; he would very fain ſee <hi>Seſtiana,</hi> and yet he would not ſee her; love her, and yet not love her, put her out of his thoughts, and yet keep her in them. <q>What, ſaid he to himſelf, reflecting upon the miſeries that his love did make him ſuffer, muſt I love the Daughter of a man, that not only hath deſired my ruin, but all whoſe actions have too much encouraged me
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:98116:59"/>to believe that he is guilty of the crime, of which he has made me twice unjuſtly ſuſpected? but what, ſaid he, entertaining himſelf ſtill with his thoughts, if <hi>Seſtianes</hi> is baſe and perfidious, <hi>Seſtiana</hi> is one the moſt generous and moſt vertuous perſons in the world; but how can ſo much virtue, and ſo much baſeneſs be found in one and the ſame blood? noe, noe, I only help to abuſe my ſelf, I fall into the ſame ſnares, that Love ſets for me, and that Tyrant who is reſolved to make me love her, makes me ſee in her ſuch vertues as ſhe has not; ſince ſhe is the Daughter of <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianes,</hi> ſhe muſt needs reſemble him, and be perfidious and wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as he is; but (alas!) though ſhe be of his blood, ſhe is ſtill one of the moſt charming perſons in the creation; the Crime of her Father has not changed the beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:98116:60"/>lineaments of her face; ſhe loves me, I ought to love her, ſince that Love can only be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paid by love. Perhaps I have done her an injury, when the crime of her Father makes me doubt her virtue; it is no new thing to ſee wicked parents have virtuous children, nor wicked children to have virtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous parents.</q> After he had ſtrengthened himſelf in this opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and had reſolutely deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined not to baniſh from his heart the love he had for <hi>Seſtiana,</hi> he fully concluded not to recri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate upon <hi>Seſtianes,</hi> but to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice his choller, and his reſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to his love. He was no ſoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ſetled in his reſolution, but he perceived <hi>Seſtianes</hi> coming up to him. That ſight awakened again his choller, and notwithſtanding the reſolution he had taken not to diſcover his reſentments to
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:98116:60"/>him, yet he could not refrain ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering theſe words to him. <q>You ought not ſaid he to him, with ſo much eagerneſs to lay hold upon all occaſions of ruining me, for fear leſt I ſhould accuſe you, and I have been ſecret, I think, for a ſufficient time, to oblige you to believe that I could ſtill be ſo. I do not know, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied <hi>Seſtianes</hi> to him, with a look full of diſdain, what it is you mean, and if I am guilty of any crime of which I ought to be accuſed it is only in your fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; but I ſhould be too blame to wonder at it, added he, what my duty has obliged me to do againſt you very likely may not inſpire you with any thing to my advantage, but revenge may poſſibly have made you ſeek out all ways to ruin me; but my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency ſecures me from all that you can ſay againſt me, and thoſe
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:98116:61"/>perſons that are diſintereſſed will ſtill know, when you ſpeak after the manner you do now, that it is only revenge which makes you capable of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving any ſuch diſcourſe: as for my part, continued he, though I am very ſorry I have loſt your friendſhip, yet I ſhall never repent my having done what I ought for the ſafety of the Prince <hi>Theomedes:</hi> we owe all to perſons of his blood, and in the like occaſion, we are o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliged to do the ſame thing for all the World. Have you that confidence to ſpeak to me in this manner, replied <hi>Democrates</hi> to him, and have you forgot what you told me ſome time before I was taken priſoner, the firſt time that I was unjuſtly ſuſpected? whatſoever I might have told you, reported <hi>Seſtianes</hi> to him with a very great aſſurance, I
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:98116:61"/>never told you I was a criminal, and if I had been ſo, and you had known it, I ſhould not have had that preſumption to carry to the King the Letter that you wrote to <hi>Anaxander;</hi> and as it was by meer accident that I met with it, I could, to ſerve you, have made it not to be ſeen, and I had done it, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt, if my duty had not obliged me to the contrary; howſoever I am extreamly over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed, that thoſe great proofs of your crime have not produced againſt you the fatall effects you could not but expect from them. But as I am not indued with leſs virtue then my Daughter, I am not willing to have for my Son-in-Law a man who is not clear'd but by favour of the crime, of which poſſibly with too much juſtice he may have been ſuſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted. I take my ſelf to be quit of
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:98116:62"/>my promiſe after what has hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened to you, and if you think I treat you too ſeverely, impute it only to your crime, or if you are innocent, impute it then to your misfortune.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Saying theſe laſt words he left <hi>Democrates,</hi> but in ſuch a condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that was enough to make the moſt hardy to fear, and to ſtir up pity in thoſe that are leaſt ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. He had a good minde to break out into the violence of his rage, and follow <hi>Seſtianes,</hi> to make him repent of his ſo inſolent diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, but the exceſs of that ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and grief into which thoſe injurious words had put him, rendered him powerleſs, and were the cauſe, that the fire and rage that was viſible in his eyes, was not able to appear in his acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Then did he ſolemnly ſwear that he would never any longer think of <hi>Seſtiana's</hi> charms, and
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:98116:62"/>the hatred he had conceived a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Father, and which had an acceſſion by his diſcourſe, made him in appearance ſtifle all the love he had for the daughter.</p>
            <p>Five or ſix days paſt in which <hi>Democrates</hi> did all he could to drive <hi>Seſtiana</hi> out of his thoughts, and that fair one all that ſhe could poſſibly think of, to forget <hi>Democrates.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the mean time <hi>Seſtianes</hi> who feared nothing from our Heroe, frequently ſaw thoſe that were of the conſpiracy with him, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered to them that the alarm which had been given the Prince <hi>Theomedes</hi> was the cauſe that he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways went well guarded, and that they muſt wait, and take up o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther meaſures then thoſe they had reſolved on. He flattered them with the hopes of a happy ſucceſs, and made them foreſee that if any of them had the confidence to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:98116:63"/>him, he could order <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſo, that the crime ſhould revert upon him, for he would ſay that he was bribed by <hi>Democrates,</hi> who accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to all appearances, ſtudied to revenge himſelf of the ſenſible af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front he had given to his honour, in preſenting the King with the letter he wrote to <hi>Anaxander;</hi> which had been eaſie for him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe none of them could give in proofs of his conſpiracy, being all ingaged only by word.</p>
            <p>But though <hi>Seſtianes</hi> feared no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing from <hi>Democrates,</hi> yet he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved not to let a perſon live who he knew very well would be his mortalenemy, after he had offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him in two ſuch tickleliſh points as are honour and love; but as nothing did engage him to precipitate his ruin, he waited till time furniſh'd him with a favour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able opportunity to ſet about it with ſafety, and without fear of
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:98116:63"/>being ever diſcovered: and being as expert in his politicks, as he was treacherous and wicked, he ſtired up <hi>Arcas,</hi> in covert words, to kill <hi>Democrates,</hi> telling him that as long as he lived, it was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for him to root him out of the heart of his Daughter, and that he would have the diſſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of knowing that ſhe loved another beſides himſelf; which ſo awakend the Jealouſie of this new Gallant, that he narrowly watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the actions of <hi>Seſtiana,</hi> to ſee if after the prohibitions of her Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to love his Rival, and ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more to ſpeak to him, her love would make her finde out any way to come to diſcourſe with him.</p>
            <p>Whilſt theſe things were hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pening, <hi>Democrates</hi> was the moſt perplexed man in the world. The love that he thought he had for ever driven out of his breaſt,
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:98116:64"/>had by degrees got in again, and ruled there with ſo much vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, that he could not finde out any ways to get the maſtery of it; which obliged him by all means imaginable to try if he could not poſſibly ſpeak with <hi>Seſtiana</hi> pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately, to learn if he was ſtill be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved by her, and to reſolve, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as ſhe treated him, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he ſhould perſevere in his Love, or continue the efforts he made, to ſtifle a flame, which ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranniſed in his breaſt with ſo ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute an Empire, and which he had ſeveral times unprofitably at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted to remove from it.</p>
            <p>After he had a good while been contriving how to come to the end of this deſign, and to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the object of his vows with that freedom he deſired, he thought it was his beſt way to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat the ſervice of one of <hi>Seſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na's</hi> relations, who had always
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:98116:64"/>teſtified to him a very great eſteem, and alſo as great a friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; and to begg of her to order it ſo, that this fair one might be one day at her houſe, that ſo he might have the happineſs of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſing with her there. <hi>Seſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi> who had an abſolute confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in this perſon, and who did as earneſtly deſire to ſpeak with <hi>Democrates,</hi> as <hi>Democrates</hi> did to ſpeak with her, made her the ſame requeſt, ſo that this Lady found it no hard matter to give them both a ſatisfaction.</p>
            <p>The day that theſe two Lovers were to ſee one another being come, they each of them reſolved, on their parts to reſiſt with all the power they could the tender ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents that Love inſpired into them; and to that end both of them left their lodgings in this reſolution, but when they were got together, a very ſmall matter
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:98116:65"/>would have made them forgot what they had reſolved upon, and have ſet them upon new proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Love: for though their deſign was fully to hate one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and to make their hatred viſible by the reciprocal teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of it; yet they were never in a leſs diſpoſition to do it. But however, <hi>Seſtiana,</hi> who had a very great aſcendent over her ſelf, and who was reſolved to be as good as her intentions, ſpoke firſt, and ſaid to <hi>Democrates,</hi> 
               <q>I would willingly demand a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of you, which I deſire you would grant me in the name of that Love which has reciprocal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reigned in both our hearts; if you ſtill love me, and if you have any kindneſs for your ſelf, you ought not to deny it me, it being a thing that will re-eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh our repoſe, and keep us from doing that which may be
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:98116:65"/>ſhamefull to us; it is a thing that will be profitable to us both, and which will ſpare us a great many ſighs: in a word, it is your hatred; I do whatſoever I can to give you mine, but I know very well that without the help of yours all my efforts will ſignify little. This requeſt added ſhe, looking ſtedfaſtly upon him, ought not to give you ſo great a ſurpriſe as I ſee plainly by your countenance it does, for I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand nothing of you but what is juſt, you owe me your hatred, and I likewiſe owe you mine; you owe me yours, after what my Father has done againſt you; and I owe you mine, becauſe you have had the confidence to demand of me my heart, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to ſeduce it, yours being ſtained with a crime which as yet you have not been able to purge your ſelf of, but through
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:98116:66"/>the bounties of the King, and the favours of Prince <hi>Theomedes.</hi> You ſee by that, continued ſhe, that we cannot love one another without betraying our glory, and not to have a hatred for each other is to wound it, and therefore you ought to grant me yours, for the price of mine. Ah! Madam replied <hi>Democrates</hi> to her with a languiſhing voice, and an air the moſt paſſionate in the world, if there be nothing but my hatred that can draw upon me yours, I am ſure you will never hate me as long as you live; you demand that of me which is not in my power, for love and hatred are not volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry things, and if when one has once began either to love or hate, it is impoſſible any longer to be Maſter of thoſe two great and violent paſſions, it is very difficult to kindle them when
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:98116:66"/>one has not as yet began to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent them. But yet I will avow to you, if that can bring you any ſatisfaction, that my deſires were agreable to yours, that I have done whatever I could to hate you, and that it has not been poſſible for me to effect it, any more then it has been for you; which clearly ſhows that our hearts do not agree with our deſires, that they have given themſelves up abſolutely to love, and that they have not any place in them to receive hatred. Since you will not hate me, replied <hi>Seſtiana</hi> to him, I will be more generous then you, I will begin firſt to do my duty, and by my example inſpire into you thoſe ſentiments you ought to have What, Madam, anſwered <hi>Demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates,</hi> can you then reſolve to hate me, when you ought to give me the moſt ſignal marks of your
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:98116:67"/>love? Ah! let me beſeech you think of the violence I do to my ſelf for your ſake, and remember that the ardent affection I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve for you, after thoſe treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments I have received from your father, ought to make you have in my favour more pleaſant and obliging ſentiments. That ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent affection which you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve for me, after an affront which ought to be ſo ſenſible to you, replied ſhe to him, produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces more effects then you ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, for if it makes me to know the greatneſs and exceſs of your love, it at the ſame time makes me to underſtand your baſeneſs, and if according to the rule, which is, that one ſhould return love for love, it obliges me to have a kindneſs for you, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding then to that other, which is, that one ſhould look upon the baſe with contempt, it o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliges
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:98116:67"/>me to hate you. Do what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever you pleaſe, replyed this unfortunate Lover to her, I will bear all from you without mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muring, I will reſpect your choller, I will reſpect your ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, and in ſpight of all your contempts, I will conſerve for you a love ſo firm and conſtant, that there ſhall be nothing in the world capable to ſhake it. Well then! anſwered this Generous Heroin Lover, ſince you force me to acknowledg a weakneſs, which ſhall never be of advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage to you, I do love you, I own it, and though I would, yet I cannot oblige my heart to hate you; but in ſpight of all that love that this perfidious heart will conſerve, I am going to marry <hi>Arcas,</hi> to make you know that. Ah! Madam, (inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted the miſerable <hi>Domocrates,</hi> whom thoſe words had almoſt
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:98116:68"/>rendered immoveable,) what crime have committed that can oblige you to puniſh me with ſo much rigour? hate me rather, for heav'ns ſake, then love me in this manner. So long as you ſhall hate me, I ſhall hope al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways that my love, and my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects may be able one day to o'recome your hatred, and ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der me poſſeſſor of one of the fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt perſons in the world; but when I ſhall ſee you in the arms of <hi>Arcas,</hi> I ſhall only hope from death to derive the end of all my pains and ſufferings. Yet if you knew, purſued he, fetch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a deep ſigh, what I do for your repoſe, and if you knew the tears, and the cruel afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons I keep from you, I am ſure you would treat me with leſs ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour; but whatſoever the evils that my ſilence cauſes me, your repoſe is too dear to me not
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:98116:68"/>to preferr it to mine; I ſhould be afraid I might ſee you die with regret and grief, and that fear forces me to conceal from you a ſecret which would coſt you too dear. All that I demand of you, continued he, for the reward of a ſervice, which poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly you will never know the greatneſs of, and which proceeds only from an exceſs of love and generoſity, is that you would not marry <hi>Arcas.</hi> You would then, interrupted <hi>Seſtiana,</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blige me to pay a ſervice without knowing it, and even without knowing whether it be true that you have rendered me any or no. Ah! Madam, cryed <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mocrates,</hi> interrupting he rin his turn, this ſervice has ſomewhat ſo particuler in it, that I cannot render it to you, and diſcover it to you both together; the one is incompatible with the other,
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:98116:69"/>and if I told it you, I ſhould not then render it to you. Since that this ſecret is of ſo great impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, replied this charming perſon to him, I will not oblige you to reveal it, and ſhow my ſelf curious, as the generality of my ſex do, for fear my curioſity ſhould be puniſhed, and I ſhould repent my earneſtneſs in preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing you to diſcover it. This diſcourſe, replied <hi>Democrates</hi> to to her, does not ſurpriſe me, I knew long ſince how much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove other women you were, and that you do nothing where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in there is not an extraordinary height of prudence to be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; but in ſhort, Madam, as this vertue is not repugnant to that which I demand of you, and and that it does not oblige you to betray me, let me beſeech you to tell me, what it is you would have me to hope for, and
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:98116:69"/>if you are reſolved to marry, —Ah! let us not diſcourſe any longer, ſaid the fair Lady inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupting him, either of love, or of marriage, do not force me if you love me, to diſcover my weakneſs to you and do not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain me to betray my virtue. When you were without a Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val, I did not finde it ſo difficult to teſtify my choller to you; but now I muſt complain of you in ſpite of all my reſiſtance; my heart will not let me reſolve to hate you, but ſpeaks to me in your favour, and tells me you will coſt me not a few tears. I do not know whence this melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly foreknowledge proceeds, but I perceive very well that pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty does intereſs it ſelf as much for you, as Love; and indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to ſtifle all thoſe ſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments I ought to have to your diſadvantage. Do not enquire
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:98116:70"/>any further, anſwered-our He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roe, from whence thoſe ſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of love and pity proceed, that ſpeak to you ſo much in my favour, my Love and my inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence without doubt are the cauſe of them, and thereby do advertiſe you, not to betray in marrying <hi>Arcas,</hi> the moſt faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and moſt paſſionate of all Lovers; becauſe that when you come to be convinced of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocence, the death you will have brought upon him by your cruel carriage, will oblige you to beſtow upon him ſome tears.</q> The Lady ſtaid till then without pouring out any, but at thoſe ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry words ſhe could not forbear ſhedding a few, which ſhe ming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with thoſe ſighs that at the ſame time broke from her, and immediately took her leave of him, not to give him the ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction he might have derived from
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:98116:70"/>the pleaſureableneſs of a frailty which was of ſo much advantage to him: but ſhe told him as ſhe was going away, that if ſhe could make her duty to agree with her Love, he might aſſure himſelf that ſhe would do whatſoever he deſired her, and that ſhe would never marry <hi>Arcas. Democrates,</hi> after he had this anſwer, return'd back again, but not ſo well ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied as he would have been, if he had had a leſs knowledge of the power that <hi>Seſtiana</hi> had over her ſelf, for he was ſenſible that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though this generous perſon had more then an ordinary kindneſs for him, yet ſhe would ſacrifice her love to her duty, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience ſhe owed to her Father would make her to marry his Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val, though indeed ſhe had never ſo great an averſion to him.</p>
            <p>As this Lover, whoſe heart was divided between hope and
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:98116:71"/>fear, was going to his lodgings, he found an occaſion to exerciſe his valour, for he met with a nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous troop of ſeditious perſons, who had conſpired the ruin of all the <hi>Houſe Royal.</hi> He put himſelf in the head of the Soldiers whom the King had ſent to ſeize thoſe Traitours and perfidious ſubjects, and to puniſh, by a ſudden death, thoſe they could not arreſt. <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mocrates</hi> animated them in ſuch a manner by his courage and words, that they wrought mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles by his Example, and brought back five hundred of thoſe ſediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous fellows priſoners.</p>
            <p>The King having heard what was done, received our Heroe with a tenderneſs as you may eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly imagine, and the Prince <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medes,</hi> who was no leſs obliged to him then the King, in as much as the conſpiracy reſpected all the <hi>Houſe Royal,</hi> teſtifyed to him the
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:98116:71"/>eſteem he had of his valour.</p>
            <p>And whilſt love and fortune were treating <hi>Democrates</hi> in a more civil and obliging manner then they had done before for I know not how long, fear began to take a violent poſſeſſion of the heart of <hi>Seſtianes.</hi> He could not tell what was become of one of thoſe who joined with him in the conſpiracy againſt Prince <hi>Theomedes,</hi> and as it was he of all the number whom he moſt miſtruſted, his abſence gave him ſo great an inquietude as would be very difficult to expreſs, unleſs one could be ſenſible of all that fear produces in the hearts of cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minals that are afraid of being diſcovered.</p>
            <p>But as there is nothing can be kept ſo ſecret long, as to be a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve from jealous Lovers, <hi>Arcas,</hi> who had very faithfull ſpies, was ſoon informed that <hi>Seſtiana</hi> had
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:98116:72"/>had a long diſcourſe with <hi>Demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates</hi> at one of her coſins houſes. He immediately complained to her Father of it, who was glad to hear it, &amp; aſſured him that for the future he would ſo order things, as they ſhould not be able to finde out any way for a converſation. He would have made the ſame complaint to <hi>Seſtiana,</hi> but ſhe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd it in ſuch a manner, as made him know that his love &amp; his jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie were both indifferent to her and that he would find it a hard matter to root out of her breaſt a Rival who had made himſelf Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of it, and who had long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore obtained her eſteem, and had ſurprized her tendereſt affections. There was very little wanting, to make this Lover, who abandoned himſelf to his diſpair, loſe that reſpect which is due to ſo char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming a Sex, and to ſpeak like one that is jealous, and a husband, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:98116:72"/>of ſpeaking like an inamou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Gallant: and the violence he did himſelf in retaining his jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous tranſports, made him go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from this fair and ſcornful Lady, full of an extraordinary deſpite, and ſo furious a jealouſie, that as ſoon as he was got within his own doors, he wrote a chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge to <hi>Democrates,</hi> to oblige him to fight him the next day.</p>
            <p>Our Heroe was too generous not to meet at this aſſignation of honour, and indeed he was firſt at the place, which <hi>Arcas</hi> had appointed. That Rival, whom deſpite and choller animated, came thither a little after. They were not long before they had their ſwords in their hands, and were ingaged; and they immediately, by the paſſes they made, gave one another the mutual marks of their valour, but at laſt, you muſt know (without any neceſſity of my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:98116:73"/>to you the manner of their combat, which I was no eye witneſs of) that <hi>Arcas</hi> was forced to ask his life of <hi>Democra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,</hi> and to promiſe him that he would never marry <hi>Seſtiana.</hi> Fame quickly ſpread this news abroad, and <hi>Seſtianes</hi> was as much afflicted at it, as his daughter had joy, and the whole Court commended <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mocrates,</hi> and eſteemed his pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, in that he had given life to a man of the quality of <hi>Arcas,</hi> and who had in the opinion of all the world ſuch relations and friends as would moſt certainly revenge his death.</p>
            <p>But whilſt hope began to repoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs the heart of <hi>Democrates,</hi> and likewiſe he to feel the joy that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune never gave him but for a few moments, and only to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage new miſeries, <hi>Arcas</hi> felt what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever rage and deſpair make thoſe indure who are violently
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:98116:73"/>tormented with them, and a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle more would have made him revenge upon himſelf the injuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and ſenſible affront that fate had put upon him.</p>
            <p>If thoſe two Lovers reſented, the one joy, and the other grief, <hi>Seſtiana</hi> ſingly reſented both; for if <hi>Democrates</hi>'s victory gave her the former, ſhe was greatly trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in that ſhe could not ſee him, nor have the libertie to ſpeak with him, and the aſſurance that her father gave her, that he would never conſent ſhe ſhould marry him, in a great meaſure allay'd the joy ſhe had at firſt conceived from the victory of that dear and faithful Lover.</p>
            <p>But as misfortune, which ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver obſerves any meaſures in the evils it cauſes, when it has once begun to make a perſon feel the rigour of its moſt cruel and pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing malice, and which was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:98116:74"/>that our illuſtrious and generous Heroe ſhould be expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to the grievous and terrible ſeverity of its aſſaults, and that the unfortunate <hi>Democrates</hi> ſhould not long make her waver between joy and ſadneſs; though ſhe was in a condition much more capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to raiſe pitty, then ſtir up en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy, for the joy ſhe had was ſo far from cauſing the effects it was wont to produce, that it only ſerved to make her the more ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of the unjuſt and tormenting pains of her deſtiny; it found that ſhe was ſtill too favourably dealt with, and that her grief ought not to be mixt with any joy at all, nor with any hopes of ever being able to get out of it, nor ſo much as to ſee it leſſen and decay; and therefore made her know with as much diligence, as thoſe, who thought they brought good news, could inform her, that the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:98116:74"/>and unfortunate <hi>Democrates</hi> had been cruelly aſſaſſinated the precedent evening, as he was go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from his lodgings to wait up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Prince, by three men un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known, who after they had gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven him ſeveral mortal wounds, with all the haſt they could, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took themſelves to their heels for ſafety, and they proved ſo ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to them, that thoſe who had purſued them, were not able ſo much as to learn any news of them.</p>
            <p>The generous and faithful Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver of the unfortunate <hi>Democrates</hi> had no ſooner heard this ſad and fatal truth, but the lively exceſs of that grief ſhe reſented at it, ſo vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olently ſeized upon her, that at firſt ſhe was not able to complain of her fate for a loſs that was ſo ſenſible to her; but as ſoon as the trouble into which this dreadful news had put her, was a little diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſipated,
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:98116:75"/>and her grief had given her leaſure to reflect upon the new calamities that her unhappi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs had brought upon her, and to think of the death of a perſon to whom ſhe had given her heart, ſhe diſcovered, by her ſighs and tears, and by her complaints, that notwithſtanding the ardent affection <hi>Areas</hi> had for her, and the commands that her father had laid upon her to be favourable to it, ſhe had ſtill had a kindneſs for <hi>Democrates,</hi> and that ſhe did yet love him even after his death.</p>
            <p>Though <hi>Seſtiana</hi> was in one of the ſaddeſt and deplorable condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in the world; though her miſeries were extream, and one would think that nothing was ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of giving them any acceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, yet her cruel deſtiny, which was not weary of perſecuting her, had, in cauſing the death of <hi>Democrates,</hi> prepared new matter
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:98116:75"/>to increaſe the grief of this il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrious miſerable Lady; and to redouble her tears; ſince that thoſe, who confirmed to her the death of her Lover, told her like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe that thoſe Aſſaſſines having thought him dead, after they had given him ſo many wounds, had betook themſelves to their heels, and that <hi>Democrates</hi> had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo yet ſo much ſtrength as to ſpeak to thoſe who were come to his relief, and to tell them that the condition in which he was, obliged him to inform the King and Prince <hi>Theomedes</hi> that he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved <hi>Sestianes</hi> was the Author of the conſpiracy againſt the latter of them, and that the Love he had for the divine <hi>Seſtiana,</hi> had kept him from making any diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of it. They alſo added, that after he had pronounced the name of <hi>Seſtiana,</hi> thoſe ſighs which Love had made him fetch,
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:98116:76"/>joined to the extream weakneſs, that the loſs of his blood had put him into, for ſome time had kept him from ſpeaking; but at laſt he had ſaid with much ado, that he was not fully aſſured that <hi>Seſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes</hi> was guilty, but that he had very powerfull indications of it, and that Prince <hi>Theomedes</hi> ought only to make uſe of his words, to conſtrain him, in caſe he was a criminal, to diſcover all himſelf, after he had got him arreſted, or at leaſt but to oblige that Prince to miſtruſt him, and to take heed that he does not expoſe himſelf to the fury of his aſſaults.</p>
            <p>It is impoſſible to repreſent well to you the eſtate of the affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted <hi>Seſtiana,</hi> after ſhe had heard of this new misfortune. Fear, deſpite, hatred, Love and grief had their ſeveral combats in her, from which ſhe never got with any advantage, but the end of
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:98116:76"/>them was always fatall to her re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. Fear made her apprehend ſomething that would be of very ill conſequence to her Father; deſpite and hatred made her hate him, whom love for all that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced her ſtill to have a kindneſs for, though he was only fit for his grave; and grief made her be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wail him whom ſhe deteſted. Her ſighs were divided between love and Nature, ſhe gave ſome to the future unhappineſs of her Father, and ſome ſhe beſtowed on her Lover, and if ſhe was not to be comforted for the loſs of him, thoſe words he uttered dying a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt her Father, afflicted her yet more. She loved him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wailed him, and hated him alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether: ſhe hearkned to her du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, ſhe followed the ſentiments that love inſpired into her, and at the ſame time gave ſomewhat too to her deſpite; but though
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:98116:77"/>ſhe did what ſhe could to content them all, yet her mind was no whit the leſs quiet nor her affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions leſs great and cruel, and grief got abſolute miſtriſs of her ſoul, and tormented it with all the rigor and ſeverity that it is wont to make uſe of when it has a mind to give a cruel perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to thoſe whom it undertakes to make moſt miſerable, by put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them into a condition never to be able to injoy a moments re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Democrates</hi>'s words at dying were quickly carried to the King, and to Prince <hi>Theomedes,</hi> who were no leſs ſurpriſed at them, then at the death of that generous unfortunate man. They were both very hard to believe that <hi>Seſtianes</hi> ſhould be guilty, and what he had done outwardly for <hi>Theomedes,</hi> in giving to the King the letter that <hi>Democrates</hi> had writ
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:98116:77"/>to <hi>Anaxander,</hi> kept that Prince from giving any credit to that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation againſt him. But yet as nothing is dearer to us than life, which ought to be kept with the greateſt care, he was reſolved to let him be atreſted if he was to be found, that ſo he might be the better ſatisfied of the truth of it, and to ſee if his looks would not betray him, and if his ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe of finding himſelf a priſoner would not make him confeſs a crime of which he was only ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected by force, or make him do what he could to the contrary, give ſome manifeſtations of it, &amp; deſigned at the ſame time to ſet him at liberty, if he did not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg any thing, without forcing him by any wrack or tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to declare himſelf guilty. But it was not the love he had for <hi>Seſtianes,</hi> nor any happineſs that he wiſht him, obliged him to act
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:98116:78"/>after this manner; but what he thought he had done to ſerve him, in accuſing <hi>Democrates,</hi> who was to have been his Son in-Law, had much leſſened the ſeverity he would have had towards him, and ingaged him to treat him ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerouſly, at leaſt until he might have ſome proofs of the attempt of which he was accuſed.</p>
            <p>Prince <hi>Theomedes</hi> was in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, and had already deſired the King to permit <hi>Seſtianes</hi> to be arreſted, and to go out of priſon a little while after, if he ſhould not confeſs himſelf a criminal, and if no other more convincing proofs could be alledged againſt him of his crime then the laſt words of <hi>Democrates,</hi> which did not poſitively conclude him guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, when that <hi>Seſtianes</hi> was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up to them where they were. The King, and Prince <hi>Theomedes</hi> were greatly ſurprized to ſee him,
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:98116:78"/>for they could not doubt but that he had heard of the laſt words of <hi>Democrates,</hi> which were ſpoke be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore too great a multitude not to have been reported to him, and they were perſwaded that he would rather have thought upon flying, then upon coming thither. But this perfidious wretch was too ſubtil too have conceived any ſuch deſign that would have been ſo prejudicial to him, and he had not reſolved to betray himſelf. <q>I come, ſaid he to them with a countenance that ſeemed not to have the leaſt concern upon it in the world, and with as great an aſſurance in his voice; to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der my ſelf a priſoner, to juſtifie me of what <hi>Democrates</hi> has ſaid of me dying: had I been crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, I ſhould not with ſo much confidence dare now to appear before you, I ſhould have been by this time far enough off of
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:98116:79"/>this place, and have had time e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to make my eſcape from the juſt chaſtiſement that would have been due to me; but I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to prove it a meer impoſture, and ſo ſhow my innocence, for it is only virtue that is the cauſe of my crime.</q> Yes, my virtue is all that has rendered me guilty; ſince that, continued he, addreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing himſelf to Prince <hi>Theomedes,</hi> 
               <q>what I lately did for you, in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering the Letter that <hi>Demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates</hi> was ſending to his friend, was the occaſion of his reſolving to do what he could to make my innocence be ſuſpected, and to be revenged for my making his to be called in queſtion. It is well known how ſweet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge is, and what it will prompt a man to do; what ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects it produces daily; that there are ſome perſons who find it impoſſible to ſtifle the ſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:98116:79"/>it inſpires them withal; that there are ſome with whom it never dies; and indeed who keep it up even after death, in leaving it as an Inheritance to their Children or friends, or elce in ſaying ſuch words when they are dying, as make 'em per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute, after their death, thoſe whom they were reſolved to be revenged of while they were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live. This revenge is oft times too deeply rooted in the hearts of men, and which of all the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions dies laſt with them: which has made <hi>Democrates</hi> to ſay that he had very powerful manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of my crime: it is clearly demonſtrable by thoſe laſt words, that he was cruelly trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with this outragious paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that it compleated his deſires, and took up all his thoughts; ſince that then when he ſhould have been only thinking on that
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:98116:80"/>great account he was going to make to the Gods of all his acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, it was only the power of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge that was able to open his mouth. Yet he had not that au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daciouſneſs poſitively to affirm that I was a Criminal, for fear leaſt his Impoſture might have been too apparent; but was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, in-ſpite of his good inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to ruin me to be contented with only making my innocence doubted of, poſſibly thinking, that in caſe his wounds ſhould not be mortal, he might be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to prove what he had ſaid. And thus you ſee, continued he, both what is my crime, and wherefore I am criminal, yet notwithſtanding my Innocence, if you ſuſpect me to be guilty, ſaid he, throwing himſelf upon his knees before the King, and Prince <hi>Theomedes,</hi> I have deſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to die, and will ſeek it with a
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:98116:80"/>paſſionate earneſtneſs, ſince I've merited your anger and whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever has had the unhappineſs to diſpleaſe Kings and Princes, and has procur'd himſelf their anger, is unworthy to live, or at leaſt deſerves to have but a languiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing life, accompanied with a thouſand miſeries, and full of melancholy fears, and torments, and inquietudes.</q>
            </p>
            <p>If the King and Prince <hi>Theome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des</hi> could not keep their ſurpriſe from being taken notice of, in ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Seſtianes</hi> coming up to them, his words made it much more vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible in their looks: they ſtood a good while ſilent, not knowing what they had beſt to doe, nor in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed what they had beſt to ſay to him; but at laſt being overcome by his artifices, they took the moſt deceitful and perfidious of all men breathing for the moſt generous, and thought it would
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:98116:81"/>be an injuſtice to queſtion his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocence, and that they ought to ſend him away with a perfect ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution; that which perſwaded <hi>Theomedes</hi> to it, was, that if he had conſpired againſt him, which he could not believe, for the reaſons I have acquainted you with, this civil treatment would oblige him poſſibly to change his deſign of killing him, into that of doing him ſervice.</p>
            <p>This crafty perfidious wretch, after he had kiſt the Kings hand and the Princes, withdrew very much ſatisfied at the favourable ſucceſs of ſo uncommon a temeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and as before ever he went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout this deviſe, he had acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his aſſoſiates with it, and bid them not to be allarmed at it, nor fear any thing, he went ſtrait from the preſence to give them an account of what had paſt, and to let them know the good for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune,
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:98116:81"/>that his addreſs and artifices bad met with, and the eſteem that the King and Prince <hi>Theomedes</hi> had of him. This intelligence did exceedingly rejoyce the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates; they thought they had no cauſe of apprehending any thing, but that they were as ſafe as could be, and that no miſchief could be fall them, it being out of the power of fortune to betray them, and ever to make them be diſcovered, having got a perſon ſo witty, ſo fortunate, and ſo couragious as <hi>Seſtianes,</hi> who was able to turn thoſe things to his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, which in all probability, would have wrought his abſolute ruin.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Seſtiana</hi> was informed with how much honour her Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was come off of the imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion he lay under, her fear began by degrees to abate, in thinking that her Father was not looked
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:98116:82"/>upon as criminal, and that he was not taken priſoner, but the more this fear grew off, the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er was her regret for the death of ſo faithfull a Lover; all her vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, though it was moſt ſeverely ſtrict, could not keep her from beſtowing ſome tears on a perſon who had like to take away her Fathers life. <q>I perceive very well, ſaid ſhe to her ſelf, if <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mocrates</hi> were ſtill living, my vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue would not ſuffer me, either to ſee him, or to love him, or ſo much as permit him to have any Love for me; but pity obliges me, do what I can, to bewail the unhappy fate of him to whom I had given my heart; none ought to wonder at it, nor ought I to wonder at it my ſelf, pity produces many other ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, and if it force us to bewail our enemies, when they are no longer in a capacity of doing us
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:98116:82"/>any hurt, none need to be amaz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, if it makes us to regret thoſe whom we have loved. I wiſh, ſaid ſhe to her ſelf, diſcourſing ſtill with her thoughts, that <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mocrates</hi> had not ſpoke againſt my Father, but has not my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſpoke againſt him, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he had promiſed he ſhould marry me, did not he deprive him of all hopes that he would ever give me his hand? I wiſh that <hi>Democrates</hi> had had thoſe ſentiments a generous per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ought to have, but he was a Man; that is to ſay, ſenſible of injuries, and beſides, an abuſed Lover, and thoſe two things do often oblige perſons to do both more then they ought, and more then they would. To conclude, I wiſh that <hi>Democrates</hi> had not done what an Heroick, but what a ſevere and ſcrupulous virtue inſpires in thoſe who poſſeſs it
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:98116:83"/>in the ſupremeſt degree; but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge, that cruel imperious paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, which always governs with an abſolute Empire the hearts of thoſe it has got the power over, and which has as little reaſon to qualify it as love, and beſides is full as blinde; that Tyrant of Souls did force him, in ſpight of all his reſiſtance, to prefer its councells to thoſe of generoſity.</q> Theſe were the ſentiments of <hi>Seſtiana,</hi> who im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to revenge all that <hi>Democra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes</hi> had ſpoke againſt her Father, and who never yet ſuſpected the truth, and was leſs diſpoſed to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine it, for it is very rare for a child to doubt the innocence of thoſe who are the occaſion of their coming into the world.</p>
            <p>But although <hi>Democrates</hi> was almoſt univerſally lamented, and his friends took his death with a great deal of grief, which was
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:98116:83"/>likewiſe bewailed moſt paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately by her, who notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſeverity of her virtue, had not the power to hate him, yet his death was not left to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puniſhed, though they were ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of the Authors of it. Not but that <hi>Arcas</hi> was ſuſpected of it; but the want of ſufficient proof, together with his eminent quality, kept the relations of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mocrates</hi> from diſcovering their reſentment and revenge, as much as they had done, had they known that another had been the Author of ſo foul and baſe an action, or had they had any ſufficient proofs againſt thoſe who had been ſo, to which there might have been ſome credit given.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seſtianes</hi> began to hope for a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable ſucceſs of his barbarous and cruel deſign; he thought he had blown over all the ſtorms that threatned him, that he was
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:98116:84"/>not likely to be expoſed to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe of fortune, and that the eſteem the Prince <hi>Theomedes</hi> teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied to him, would give him a more convenient opportunity to execute what he had reſov'd upon when the Court received a Letter from <hi>Anaxander,</hi> whom fame, &amp; the particular friends of <hi>Democra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,</hi> had informed of all that had paſt. This ſad and generous friend of our Heroe, who ſtudied to be revenged of his death, ſent word that it was no longer neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to keep things in diſguiſe, and that he was Innocent of the crime, of which he had impeach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed himſelf, to ſave a friend, who was no more a Criminal then he or the cleareſt perſon alive; but that he was very ſure that what <hi>Democrates</hi> had ſaid againſt <hi>Seſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes</hi> after he had received his deaths wound, was moſt certainly true, that the love he had for his
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:98116:84"/>Daughter, was the occaſion that he did not diſcover it ſooner, and that the Father of that fair One ſuſpecting our Heroe knew of his crime, had accuſed him purely out of fear, that ſo if it ſhould happen to him to be accuſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, he might have a very fair plea for himſelf, and make the world believe that what he ſhould ſpeak was only out of malice and revenge. He added alſo that his friend had given him a full ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of all theſe things a little before that fatal accident befell him, and in the ſame letter ſent all the particulars that made <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mocrates</hi> to ſuſpect <hi>Seſtianes,</hi> and what he had ſaid before he was taken priſoner the firſt time. Moreover he offered to come, if they deſired it, to render himſelf a priſoner to maintain what he ſaid, and to defend the honour of his friend after his death as well
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:98116:85"/>as he had done when he was li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, and earneſtly petitioned the King to let <hi>Seſtianes</hi> be arreſted to force him to diſcover all, and ſhewed him that he ſhould not run the hazard of committing an injuſtice, in caſe he did act in that manner; ſo long as it was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways in his power to reſtore him his libertie, if he judg'd him to be innocent, but that it was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to have him arreſted for the ſafety of Prince <hi>Theomedes</hi>'s life; becauſe he knew of no other Criminals but him, and that what he had ſaid, after he had ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed himſelf for fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing the life and honour of his friend, was only that the true guilty perſons, whom yet he did not know, might not live in any ſecurity, and that the Prince <hi>Theomedes</hi> might not remain any longer ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to their fury.</p>
            <p>This Letter was preſented to
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:98116:85"/>the King with as much faithfull<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs as ſecrecy, and was peruſed by him and <hi>Theomedes</hi> without <hi>Seſtianes</hi>'s knowing any thing of it in the world. It gave them a very great confuſion, and before they ever went about making <hi>Seſtianes</hi> to be arreſted, they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined into the whole life of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mocrates,</hi> to ſee if he had never been guilty of any action misbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming a Gallant man, and which might give them any cauſe not to believe him. They likewiſe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſame account looked over all the actions of <hi>Anaxander,</hi> and whatever they had known of him, during the time he had made his reſidence in that Court; but they found nothing in nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of them that did not very highly commend their virtue, and their generoſity, and which did not perſwade them to give an intire belief to all their words.
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:98116:86"/>They alſo reflected upon all they knew of <hi>Seſtianes;</hi> but they were ſenſible upon ſeveral occaſions, that he had given them ſome cauſe of doubting his virtue; and they believed that ſince <hi>Democra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes</hi> had never given them any of miſtruſting his with juſtice, and that he accuſed him at a time, when perſons are wont to ſpeak the truth more then at any other time; upon the whole, they thought they were obliged to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve <hi>Seſtianes</hi> guilty: all theſe things conſidered with what they began to be perſwaded of that he had poſſibly blinded them by a falſe and pretended ſemblance of virtue, and that his generoſity was only an artifice to dazle them, and to divert the blow that threatned him, made them reſolve to have him taken, and be clapt up in the Tower, where none might be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to diſcourſe with him,
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:98116:86"/>which they immediately cauſed to be put in execution.</p>
            <p>Though he was not a little ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priz'd to ſee himſelf become a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner, yet he had ſo much wit with him as to conceal his inward diſorder, and though fear had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken full poſſeſſion of his heart, yet his countenance did ſhew all the tranquillity imaginable, and as he perceived they had no proofs againſt him, and had only put him into priſon to ſee if he would not betray himſelf, he defended himſelf ſo admirably, that he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived all thoſe who in the leaſt thought any thing to his diſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage. He was demanded why, upon the report that ran up and down, that <hi>Democrates</hi> knew all the Conſpiracy, he had told him, that he was unjuſtly ſuſpected, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept he had always apprehended him, or had heard that he ſhould be accuſed by him. They added
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:98116:87"/>alſo, that if he was not guilty, he ſhould not have made ſuch a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, and that whether either he had ſuſpected him, or had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally told him that he was a Crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, or that he pretended he had heard it, there was ſtill an equal ground to doubt his Innocence; ſince if that was true which was told to <hi>Democrates,</hi> that he was guilty, of neceſſity there was a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of it, and likewiſe ſome proofs of his crime, and if it was not, in all probability he only came to ſound him, and to endeavour to know cunningly of him, if it were true or not, that he was acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with all the conſpiracy, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the better to order his affairs. <hi>Seſtianes</hi> anſwered, that nothing of all this was true, and that if he had been to wait upon <hi>Democrates,</hi> to hold ſuch a diſcourſe with him, he ſhould not have dared to act a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, as he had done, for
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:98116:87"/>fear he ſhould have recriminated upon him, and that ſince he had ſaid nothing of it all the time he lived, whilſt it was ſuppoſed that he had ſaid thoſe things to him, which very likely would have ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ined him, and that he had not ſo much as ſpoke of them when he was dying, it was very eaſie to ſee that it was a meer falſity that was imputed to him. He added that it was no wonder if <hi>Anaxander</hi> did ſeek to take away his life, for ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving put into the hands of the King the letter that <hi>Democrates</hi> writ to him, that he had done things much more conſiderable to ſecure the reputation of his friend, and that ſince he had ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered himſelf guilty for his ſake, though he was Innocent, he might very eaſily be induced to tell a lye to be revenged of a perſon who had acted againſt him, who was not able to bear his crime without
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:98116:88"/>horror, and who likewiſe could not refrain ſhowing the proofs he had of it.</p>
            <p>Never were perſons ſeen in a greater perplexity and confuſion then were the King and Prince <hi>Theomedes,</hi> after they had heard the anſwer that <hi>Seſtianes</hi> made, they were clearly of opinion that he might juſtly be ſuſpected, but they did not ſee which way he could be convicted, and as all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>babilities ſignifie nothing with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out poſitive proofs, and that it is a moſt unjuſt thing to condemn a perſon upon a bare ſuſpicion, they could not tell how in the world to get out of this trouble that <hi>Seſtianes</hi> put them into by his confidence, and undaunted reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution. <q>What, ſaid Prince <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>omedes,</hi> muſt I confound the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent with the guilty, believe the moſt generous of all men are the moſt baſe, and the moſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidious
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:98116:88"/>and that the moſt perfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious &amp; baſe are the moſt gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous? muſt I think <hi>Anaxander</hi> to be an Impoſter? and muſt I think <hi>Seſtianes</hi> a wicked and perfidious wretch that has determined my death? he, who, to ſerve me, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared againſt his deſigned Son in Law? and muſt I, in a word, by a cruel neceſſity do an injury to the memory of <hi>Democrates,</hi> and doubt his Innocence, who all his life was never known to be guilty of an action unworthy an honourable perſon? But what, ſaid he again preſently, muſt I be always in fear? daily expoſed to danger, and wait till he, whoſe life I dare not yet take away, come and run me through? Yes, I ought always to be expoſed to danger and not fear the fury of thoſe who aim at my life; fear is unworthy of a Prince, and much more of a
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:98116:89"/>generous man: Princes ought not to be too careful to ſecure themſelves from the danger that threatens them, their courage and their virtue ought to be their guard, and to anſwer for what befals them, and that which is looked upon as foreſight in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, will in them be counted baſeneſs and Cowardice.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Prince <hi>Theomedes,</hi> after he had a pretty while abandoned himſelf to his inquietude, began to heark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en to thoſe ſentiments which ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neroſity uſually inſpires into per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of his Rank and Quallity, and went to demand of the King, that the moſt Criminal of all men might be ſet at liberty, when word was brought that one of the five hundred priſoners, who had been taken in the late conſpiracy, where there were ten thouſand that roſe up againſt all the Royall houſe, accuſed <hi>Seſtianes</hi> of the
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:98116:89"/>Crime, which <hi>Democrates</hi> had charged him with as he was dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. This undaunted Criminal, who was ignorant who he ſhould be, ſaid as ſoon as ever he heard of it, that this fellow was ſome cheat and impoſtor, that he did unjuſtly accuſe him, and that he would make him to confeſs the contrary, and deny all he had ſaid. Whereupon <hi>Cleobis</hi> (for ſo was that priſoner called) was brought before him; but he was greatly ſurprized when he ſaw that it was one of thoſe who had been of the conſpiracy with him, and that it was the ſame perſon, who we were mentioning be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, was miſſing, and for whom he was ſo much concerned ſince, that he knew not what was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of him, and alſo that it was him of all the Number whom he moſt ſuſpected. The ſight of him had even almoſt made him change
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:98116:90"/>his countenance, and his emoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on went very near to diſcover what he had always concealed with ſo favourable a ſucceſs. Yet notwithſtanding, his confidence having immediately baniſhed the fear that had begun to ſeize upon his heart, he looked upon <hi>Cleobis</hi> with an air full of fierceneſs and a contemning ſcorn mixt toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and ſaid with a diſdainfull ſmile; <q>though in the condition I am in at preſent, I might fear all things from my Enemies, and that the impoſture, which may juſtly be tearmed, the innocents executioner, makes uſe of all the moſt cruel and artificious ways of malice to take away my life, yet it is ſufficient to ſcarter my fear, that it is only <hi>Cleobis</hi> who preſents himſelf, and is the man that accuſes me. I do not believe the King nor the Prince <hi>Theomedes</hi> will eaſily give any
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:98116:90"/>credit to him: for any one may very well think, that if I had conſpired, I ſhould not have diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered the ſecret to a man ſo much to be miſtruſted, and it is very apparent that he does not now accuſe me, but only to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long his life, and by this artifice to hope, that Prince <hi>Theomedes,</hi> thinking himſelf greatly obliged to him, will demand his pardon of the King: I have been aſſured by ſome perſons of my acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, that my Enemies, and the Relations of <hi>Domocrates,</hi> has promiſed to get his crime par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned, provided he would ſay that which he had been ſo hardy to utter againſt me, and which he ſtill neither durſt, nor can maintain. But though all this ſhould not be true, purſued he, it is very well known that he has formerly been my greateſt Enemy, and that he was forced
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:98116:91"/>to ſeek my friendſhip. All theſe circumſtances do diſcover, that his former hatred had not now been awakened, but that he ſaw he had a moſt convenient opportunity for it; nor that he had accuſed me, but either from the proſpect he had thereby to obtain his pardon, or from the ſatisfaction he ſhould have to ſee me periſh with him; and that there ought not to be any credit given to ſuch a perſon, whom ſo many ſeveral reaſons do in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce to accuſe an innocent.</q>
            </p>
            <p>If before that <hi>Cleobis</hi> had accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>Seſtianes,</hi> the King and Prince <hi>Theomedes</hi>'s perplexity was great, this diſcourſe of that ſubtil and ingenious Politician gave a great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er acceſſion to it, and he had ſtill ſo much good fortune, that he made uſe of thoſe things which were moſt likely to ruin him, to confound others, and caſt them
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:98116:91"/>into a far greater trouble then that with which his breaſt was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitated; but at laſt that good for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune grew weary, of accompany<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo perfidious a wretch; and Heaven, which was reſolved to leave him no longer unpuniſhed, now made a truth to be known which had ſo long been kept ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret, which had given confuſion to ſo many perſons, and which untill then, could never be diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, what ever ways they had made uſe of, and notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all they had done to finde it out. But yet this wicked man had the happineſs not to betray himſelf, and ſtill ſtood it out with a great deal of wit and bravery, as long as it was poſſible for him. He did not put fortune to the bluſh for the good ſervices ſhe had done him, but he ſhowed that his bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, his conſtancy, and his wit did equal his crimes, and poſſibly
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:98116:92"/>he might yet have defended him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf longer, if that ſome of the conſpirators, whom <hi>Cleobis</hi> nam'd, had not fled for it, and if the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers had not been taken priſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, diſcovered all the particula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities, maintained to <hi>Seſtianes</hi>'s face that he was guilty, and had not by convincing proofs, and ſuch as were impoſſible to be doubted of, deprived him of all the means of defending himſelf any longer.</p>
            <p>They asked <hi>Cleobis,</hi> to be more clearly ſatisfied in all things, why he, (who had told <hi>Poligeſnes,</hi> that he would diſcover all things to him, and who was dead before he ſaw him,) had ſaid, that he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved <hi>Demotrates</hi> was of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy. <hi>Cleobis</hi> anſwered, that they had all thought ſo, for he being ſo near marrying the daughter of <hi>Seſtianes,</hi> they were fully perſwaded that he had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:98116:92"/>his deſign to him, but it ſeems that time had diſcovered to them the contrary.</p>
            <p>The perfidious <hi>Seſtianes,</hi> ſeeing himſelf convicted, yet was not at all the more allarmed at it, nor did he ſhow any actions that betray'd the conſtancy he had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways teſtifyed, he confeſt all without changing his counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and ſpoke with as much aſſurance, as if his judges had been the Criminals, and he their Judge. <q>Yes, ſaid he to them, ſince I cannot tell how any long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to defend my ſelf, I acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge I did conſpire againſt Prince <hi>Theomedes,</hi> and the ill Offices he did me at Court, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the diſpleaſure I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived in that he had given to one of his creatures a place which the King intended to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow on me, and which he had even promiſed me, did make me
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:98116:93"/>hatch the deſign of taking away his life, and for that purpoſe I elected ſuch perſons as had as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different a kindneſs for him as my ſelf, and who had as great reaſon to complain of him; and if you examine well all thoſe of the confederacy, added he, you will finde that the greateſt num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of them are thoſe that live near his lands and dominions, and whom he has by his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt tyranny, obliged to have an invincible hatred for him, and to ſtudy all ways ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable how to compaſſe his death. After this confeſſion you may imagine that <hi>Democra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes</hi> was innocent, and that I would not have deſtroy'd him but for fear leſt he ſhould accuſe me in the thoughts I had, that one of the Conſpirators had diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered all to him, and that it was only for that he had been
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:98116:93"/>ſuſpected of the crime that I was the Authour of. If <hi>Democrates,</hi> ſaid I to my ſelf, knows all, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the love he bears my daughter, will keep him from ſpeaking &amp; revealing my crime; but as there are ſeveral things that may ſtifle this love, that may make him repent of his ſilence, and at laſt hearken to his duty, when it ſhall counſel him to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover and betray me, it is my beſt way to make him undergo the ſame fate, as I have deſigned for the Prince <hi>Theomedes,</hi> and to be only thinking now how I ſhould effect it with the greateſt ſafety. I was in this reſolution, when a meer chance preſented me with the means to bring it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, more ſecret, and leſs peril<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, then thoſe were I had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to my ſelf, and gave me an opportunity to execute part of what I had projected, and
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:98116:94"/>without any blood ſhed, to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert the blow that teemed to threaten me. The letter that <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mocrates</hi> writ to <hi>Anaxander</hi> fell into my hands, and I thought it my prudenteſt courſe to put it into thoſe of the Kings, and that this ill office I ſhould do to the unfortunate Innocent perſon would prevent all manner of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of whatſoever he ſhould ſay againſt me. You have known the ſucceſs of it, but you are ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant yet that the fear of being diſcovered having taken a new poſſeſſion of my heart, and that the deſire which Ambition had kindled in me, to ſee my Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter married to <hi>Arcas,</hi> who is, as you know, both by his Eſtate, and birth, much more conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able then <hi>Democrates,</hi> obliged me to ſeek out freſh occaſions of deſtroying this latter. Fortune, which continued ſtill favoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:98116:94"/>to me, preſented me with one leſs hazardous then the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer: I knew that <hi>Arcas</hi> was cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elly perſecuted by his jealouſie, and that he could not indure my Daughter ſhould conſerve any tenderneſs for <hi>Democrates,</hi> I made uſe of this occaſion to bring my deſign about, and told him, that he ought not to ſuffer a Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val to have half ſhares of a heart which ought to belong wholly to him. As there is need of but a little thing to ſtir up a jealous man, who does not doubt but that his Rival has too great an Intereſt in the favours of his Miſtriſs, and whom <hi>Arcas</hi> his jealouſie had councell'd before to call him to an account for it, he ſtrait fought with <hi>Democrates,</hi> and in that duel met with the ſhameful ſucceſs you have heard of; which being ſo fatal to his honour, he came to give me a
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:98116:95"/>relation of his unhappineſs, and of the ſenſible diſgrace that For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune had made him receive. I knowing him then to be in a hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour fit to undertake any thing, I told him it was ſuch a ſhame to ſuffer his Rival to live any longer, and to have an object that ſhould daily repreſent to him the affront his honour had received, that without any more a doe he was reſolved to put a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riod to his days. A ſhort time af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he cauſed <hi>Democrates</hi> to be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaſſinated by three perſons whom he had hired for that purpoſe, or rather by three of thoſe merce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Aſſaſſines, who are daily employed in ſuch murders. Now, continued he, after this particular information, you ought not to ask any thing fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of me, and I have told you more then you would have known had you only learnt that
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:98116:95"/>I was the Author of <hi>Democrates</hi> his death; ſince that without my Conncel, <hi>Arcas</hi> poſſibly would never have aſſaſſinated him. This is, purſued he, a faithful account of all my crimes, and all the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour I demand of you, if you can grant any to ſo great a Criminal as I am, is to haſten the day of my death, loſt I ſhould repent that I had committed them, and that the tormenting rigour of a long &amp; cruel impriſonment ſhould a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate my conſtancy, ſo as it would do my countenance, and make thoſe who ſhould be ſpectatours at my Death, to think, that I was afraid of puniſhments, and that Death was terrible to me. I know very well, continued he, that I cannot hope for pardon, and as I would not deſire to live after I had acknowledged my ſelf a Criminal, I confeſs all my crimes, and even thoſe whereof
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:98116:96"/>I was not accuſed, that ſo the horrour you ought to have to ſuffer ſo great a Criminal to live, ſhould oblige you to give a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den determination of my death, and as ſhort a day for it.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Though <hi>Seſtianes</hi> was long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſuſpected, and even before his confeſſion they ceaſed any longer to doubt of his crime, yet his diſcourſe was very ſurprizing to thoſe Judges, as well as it ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted them with the Authour of our Heroe's Death. They cauſed him to be lockt up again, and went to inform the King and Prince <hi>Theomedes</hi> of all had paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and what <hi>Seſtianes</hi> had told them. Their aſtoniſhment could not keep them from beſtowing ſome ſighs upon the Death of <hi>Democrates,</hi> whoſe innocence thereby was fully known to them, and reflecting upon the generoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Anaxander,</hi> whom the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:98116:96"/>and confuſion in which they were, had till then kept them from eſteeming as they ought to have done; Prince <hi>Theomedes</hi> cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out, that he had never ſeen a perſon ſo generous, nor ſo faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full a friend, and that he had rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to boaſt of his crime in the firſt Letter he had ſent them, the miſterious fence of which he ſo perfectly knew, and which he had reaſon to ſay, <hi>that as bad a Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal as he declared himſelf to be, he hoped that poſterity ſhould not be able to reproach his honour;</hi> ſince that his crime was ſo glorious, and generous, that poſterity ought to conſerve the remembrance of it, to cauſe it to be admired by all thoſe that ſhould hear it.</p>
            <p>The King having underſtood, by the relation that was given him, what <hi>Seſtianes</hi> had ſaid, and heard of all the crimes he had charged himſelf with, and that
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:98116:97"/>
               <hi>Arcas</hi> had cauſed <hi>Democrates</hi> to be murthered, immediately ordered him to be arreſted; but as he was of too illuſtrious a birth, and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe had ſeveral Relations and Friends that held a very conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable rank at Court, he preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly learnt all that had paſt there, and by a haſty flight had eſcaped the priſon they had prepared for him, and ſome time after they heard that he was got into <hi>France.</hi> As for <hi>Seſtianes</hi> he had what he deſired, and was a little while after condemned to loſe his head. Prince <hi>Theomedes</hi> would never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe have uſed his utmoſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt to prevent that ſentence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his life, if he had been on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly guilty againſt him; but there was ſo much perfidiouſneſs in his crime, which came from a breaſt ſo black and wicked, that he was judged utterly unworthy to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain any favour, and that ſuch a
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:98116:97"/>perfidious and dangerous man ought not to be permitted to live, who knew how to diſſemble with ſo much art, and who was capable of accompliſhing whatſoever he undertook, which could be no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then ſuch things as muſt needs have moſt cruel and perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious conſequences.</p>
            <p>This crafty and undaunted Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal ſatisfied at the expence of his life the ſentence that had been given againſt him, and died as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt all of that Country are wont to do, that is to ſay, with a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy worthy to be admired, and ſo it was by a great number of people, who ſpoke very advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſly of his Criminal and inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious carriage, and ſaid, that he had a wit capable of the moſt dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult and hazardous enterpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</p>
            <p>That which was the more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable in this Hiſtory, was,
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:98116:98"/>that <hi>Democrates,</hi> without think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the leaſt of it, had himſelf laboured to revenge his death, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he died, and that Heaven had ſuffered <hi>Cleobis</hi> to be among the five hundred priſoners, whom that generous Heroe had helped to take, in the ſervice of his King, without knowing that among them there was a perſon, who could remove the doubt they had of his Innocence, and diſcover the real guilty perſon, and who, in re-eſtabliſhing his glory, could hinder poſterity from making his memory odious, and in a word, who could revenge his death, by the blood of the moſt perfidious man in the world.</p>
            <p>I think it is not neceſſary to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late what <hi>Seſtiana</hi> ſaid, and did, between the condemnation of her Father, and his death, nor at that time that ſhe heard of his death; for it is very well
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:98116:98"/>known than the power of grief makes one at firſt not to reſent it, that the ſurpriſe it cauſes keeps one ſilent, and that the extream weakneſs it eaſts one into, takes away the ſence. The violence of <hi>Seſtiana</hi>'s grief pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced all theſe effects, and ſhe could not reſent, and know all the calamities that were befallen her altogether, untill the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and ſeizure were a little over, which gave her ſuch fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall and ſenſible intelligences. But when ſhe was a little come to her ſelf, and in a condition of reſenting the cruel aſſaults of her grief. <q>O heavens! ſaid ſhe to her ſelf, is it poſſible you ſhould have reſolved that I ſhold indure ſo many miſeries? is it poſſible that you ſhould permit it, and can it be belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved that a poor harmleſs maid ſhould be deſtined to bear all
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:98116:99"/>the rage of the moſt barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and pittileſs fate? Ah! how did <hi>Democrates</hi> ſay to me, when I ſpoke to him of the crime which he was unjuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly accuſed of, that the guilty perſon would coſt me many tears. Both the guilty and the innocent do coſt me ſo at once; I knew not the crime of one, untill it was impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for me to prevent his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, and I did not learn the innocence of the other untill after his Death. I did not demand ſo much, nor would I have known of my Fathers crime, only have heard of the innocence of <hi>Democrates,</hi> but I would have known it, that ſo I might have recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penced it, and not have been obliged only to pour out tears. Ah! too ſenſible loſs of a dear and faithfull Lover, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:98116:99"/>what a ſad condition do you reduce me? Ah! <hi>Demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates,</hi> how will thy Death coſt me tears? ah! too blind Father, what have you done? ah! but what, purſued ſhe, am I ſenſible of what I do? I more bewail a Lover then a Father; yes, it is true, I do bewail him, and that without ſhocking either reaſon, or du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, or virtue; and though I ought to bewail them both, yet fate will have it, that he who ſhould be the deareſt to me, ſhould be the leaſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wailed. Ah! wherefore too ſcrupulous Lover, did you not diſcover your ſecret to me, I ſhould have known your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocence, and would have mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed you before my Father had forbid it; but you ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined, that I would not have believed your diſcourſes, and
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:98116:100"/>you would not put any thing to the hazard. You reſolved to be prudent, but your pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, which was almoſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal to you, has not in this oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion been more favourable then formerly. It is true it has ſpared me many diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures which poſſibly would not have been ſo cruel to me, and which perhaps I might have now forgot, and I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge this ſervice after thy death. But replied ſhe immediately, ought I to count that a Service, which makes me now to weep, and which has cauſed thy death, and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe that of my Fathers? yes, continued ſhe, it was one, but time has made it fatal, our common unhappineſs has poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned it; and prudence, which promiſes, and which affords o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſo much good fortune,
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:98116:100"/>will give us only cauſes of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicting our ſelves, and after it did make thee loſe the favour of thy Prince, kept thee from making any further declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thy flame to me, when thou mighteſt have married me, to have made me doubt your Innocence, to have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed you in all things, and to have rendered all your actions fatal to you, and at laſt to have coſt you your life, that if it had not hindered you from being the death of <hi>Arcas,</hi> that inhuman Rival had not made you be aſſaſſinated. It is impoſſible for life to be any longer pleaſing to me, after the loſs of ſo faithful a Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and it cannot but be hate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to me after the death of a Father who has loſt his head upon a Scaffold; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in honour and Love I
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:98116:101"/>ought to be ſo much the more deſirous to die, ſince it is only that which can put an end to all my cruel tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, with which my Soul will be overwhelmed as long as I have a day to live.</q>
            </p>
            <p>The ſorrow of this fair and generous afflicted Lady could not poſſibly meet with any di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minution, time which for the moſt part wears out other griefs, how cruel ſo ever, could doe nothing upon hers, till at laſt ſhe met with what ſhe ſo much deſired, which was ſo violent a Feavour, that in a few days it put an end to all her trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, as it did to her life.</p>
            <p>Five or ſix months after all theſe bloody and Tragical ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventures, they were informed that <hi>Anaxander</hi> had revenged
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:98116:101"/>the death of his friend, for ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving met <hi>Arcas</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> he obliged him to draw, in which duell he only received a ſlight wound from him, but came off a conqueror, by laying his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy dead at his feet,</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:98116:102"/>
            <head>Novels Printed for <hi>R. Bentley</hi> and <hi>M. Magaes.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>Zelinda, <hi>a Romance. 12</hi>d.</item>
               <item>Happy Slave <hi>in 3. parts compleat, 2</hi>s. <hi>6</hi>d.</item>
               <item>Heroine Muſquiteer, <hi>in 4. parts com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat, 3</hi>s.</item>
               <item>Cheating Gallant, <hi>12</hi>d.</item>
               <item>Diſorders of Love, <hi>12</hi>d.</item>
               <item>Triumphs of Love over fortune, <hi>12</hi>d.</item>
               <item>Almanzor and Almanzaid, <hi>12</hi>d.</item>
               <item>Double Cuckold, <hi>12</hi>d.</item>
               <item>Obliging Miſtriſs, <hi>12</hi>d.</item>
               <item>Colona's Memoirs, <hi>1</hi>s<hi>6</hi>d.</item>
               <item>Fatal Prudence, <hi>1</hi>s 6d.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>In the Preſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>The Princeſs of Cleves.</item>
               <item>The Theatre of the World.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>Some French Books.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:98116:102"/>
            <pb n="158" facs="tcp:98116:103"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="159" facs="tcp:98116:103"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="160" facs="tcp:98116:104"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="161" facs="tcp:98116:104"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="162" facs="tcp:98116:105"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="163" facs="tcp:98116:105"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="164" facs="tcp:98116:106"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="165" facs="tcp:98116:106"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="166" facs="tcp:98116:107"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="167" facs="tcp:98116:107"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="168" facs="tcp:98116:108"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="169" facs="tcp:98116:108"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="170" facs="tcp:98116:109"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="171" facs="tcp:98116:109"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="172" facs="tcp:98116:110"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="173" facs="tcp:98116:110"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="174" facs="tcp:98116:111"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="175" facs="tcp:98116:111"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="176" facs="tcp:98116:112"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="177" facs="tcp:98116:112"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="178" facs="tcp:98116:113"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="179" facs="tcp:98116:113"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="180" facs="tcp:98116:114"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="181" facs="tcp:98116:114"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="182" facs="tcp:98116:115"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="183" facs="tcp:98116:115"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="184" facs="tcp:98116:116"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="185" facs="tcp:98116:116"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="186" facs="tcp:98116:117"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="187" facs="tcp:98116:117"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="188" facs="tcp:98116:118"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="189" facs="tcp:98116:118"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="190" facs="tcp:98116:119"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="191" facs="tcp:98116:119"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="192" facs="tcp:98116:120"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="193" facs="tcp:98116:120"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="194" facs="tcp:98116:121"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="195" facs="tcp:98116:121"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="196" facs="tcp:98116:122"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="197" facs="tcp:98116:122"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="198" facs="tcp:98116:123"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="199" facs="tcp:98116:123"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:98116:124"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:98116:124"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
